<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A dialogue betweene a vertuous gentleman and a popish priest [ ... ]pleasaunt and profitable, both for ministers and gentlemen, men and vvomen, old and yong, made by I.B.</title>
            <author>I. B., fl. 1581.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1581</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 216 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00276</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1039</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120239</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855438</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855438</idno>
            <idno type="VID">176516</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00276)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176516)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 409:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A dialogue betweene a vertuous gentleman and a popish priest [ ... ]pleasaunt and profitable, both for ministers and gentlemen, men and vvomen, old and yong, made by I.B.</title>
                  <author>I. B., fl. 1581.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[160] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Waldegraue, dwelling without Temple-barre, neere vnto Sommerset-House,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1581.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-K.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Dialogue, betweene a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Gentleman and a popiſh prieſt, verie pleaſaunt and profitable, both for miniſters and gentlemen, men and vvomen, old and yong, made by I. B.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London, by Robert Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>degraue, dwelling without Temple-barre, neere vnto Sommcrſet-Houſe.</p>
            <p>1581.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Scriptural_citations">
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:2"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Deut. 6.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The words which I commaund thee this day, ſhall be in thine heart, and thou ſhalt reherſe them continually vnto thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and shalt talke of them when thou tarriest in thine houſe, and as thou walkest by the way, and when thou lyest down, and when thou riſest vp.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Leui. 19.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Thou ſhalt not hate thy brother in thine heart, but thou shalt playnely rebuke thy neighbour, and ſuffer him not to ſinne.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ezech. 34.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Wo be vnto the shepherds of Iſrael, that feede themſelues: shoulde not the shepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards feede the flocks.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſai. 5.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Wo bee vnto them that drawe iniquitie with cordes of vanity, and ſinne as with carte ropes.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:2"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>To the worſhipfull, and</hi> his very good Maſter, maſter H. S. Eſquire <hi>I. B. wiſheth the fauour of God, the</hi> faith of Abraham, the vviſdome of Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, the patience of Iob, a vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous lyfe in this tranſitory world, and a heauenly kingdome in the vvorlde that neuer ſhall haue end.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecauſe there can not bee a better worke taken in hand, and not mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter may haue ſo good ſucceſſe, or any time be ſo well beſtovved, as that which is ſpent in ſeeking to ſet forth the glory of god: therfore for mine own part, when I did ſee the ſlackneeſſe of many, the looſe líuing of the moſt part, and fewe or none, to ſeke for, or ſet forth thoſe things that might redound to the praiſe of God: although of al others moſt vnable, (yet as one lamenting the miſerable condition of the multitude) haue done that which in me didly, that God might be honoured, true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion imbraced, and vice ſuppreſſed and troden vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foot: and ſory I am that it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath now fallen out for my lot to play this part, for I had rather to haue ſcene it of ſome other that might haue done it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:176516:3"/>then my ſelfe, but I do vvel perceiue it to be the ſolly of many of thoſe that thinke them ſelues vviſe men, rather to beſtovve their knovvledge vvhere it ſhall little profite, then vvell to vſe that good talent that God hath lent them, they haue vvit ynough to get them ſelues promotion, they are skillul ynough to vvaxe riche in the vvorld, and they know how to do al things, ſaue that they ſhoulde: the vviſedome of God is counted neere madneſſe, the preaching of the<note n="*" place="margin">Cor. 1.18.</note> croſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, to them that periſh, fooliſhneſſe, to feare God is counted a life by it ſelfe, and ſuch as the proude Rabbies of this vvorlde, yea, and ſuch as can teach others, in this matter, are to learne many things them ſelues: it is this worlde that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, the vvorlde to come they are not for, ſo they may aduaunce them ſelues, they care not thoughe the glorye of God fall to the grounde, they liue as though there were an imortallitie to be found here on earth, and that their dwellinges ſhould continue for euer: if they may be rich in ſubſtaunce, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde not hovv farre they be behind hande in god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines: ſo they haue pleaſure and hearts eaſe here a vvhile, they may haue as it were (to buy it) laide their ſouls to pawne for the ſame. This is true, yea and too <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rue, if it pleaſed God better to diſpoſe vs, and that their madneſſe maye manifeſtly appeare: and that greeuous ſinners may feare to offende. I haue layde vvide open their ſhame, and diſplaying their vngodly behauiour, that they may ſee vvhat daunger they are in that liue vngodly, &amp; that there is no man ſo godly, as he that<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 91.1.</note> dwelleth vnder the defence of the almighty. And hauing finiſhed that I tooke in hand, I knevv not vnto whom I might ſo vvell offer the fruits of this my labour, as vnto your
<pb facs="tcp:176516:3"/>vvorſhip, vvhome experience hath taught mee to be a fauourer of the trueth, a deteſter of vice, and to nourish vertue in your breſts, as that which you dea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſt loue. In this little rreatiſe you ſhall ſee the great vvickednes of our time diſplayed, betweene a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Gentleman, and a Popish Prieſt, you shal find in the Gentleman, his talke and behauior bo bee ſuch, as may be an example to the moſt part, in theſe our daies, his vertuous talke, and ſtrong perſuaſions, with ſure warrant out of the vvorde of God, that it will make the hearts of all Popish Prieſts: and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous miniſters, if they be not as hard as the adamant ſtone, to yeeld to the ſweete dropping of his ſugred words: and contrarily in the Prieſt, the very picture of a poyſoned life, with wordes full of vanitie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the aboundaunce of a corrupt heart, vvhich vvould not yeeld vnto any perſuaſions, nor hearken to any inſtructions of a long time, before the vvord wrought vvith him more mightily, that at the length he was contented to amende his maners and to forſake three benefices vvhich he did vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully poſſeſſe, and to become a new man, and ſpende the reſt of his daies in the ſeruice of God. I vviſhe all proud Prelates and Popiſh prieſtes, vvoulde cut their coates by the ſame paterne, &amp; learne to repent by his example, and leaue their ſinnes in ſeaſon, loſt as they haue plovved vvickednes, ſo they ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> iniquitie. Let no man thinke euil of me, for whiſhing of them vvell, if they vvill count him an enemy, that vvould giue them good counſell, or couer their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ig leaues of ſhamefulneſſe, or thinke them ſelues giltleſſe, vvheras they are faulty, here is as much ſayde for them, as they can ſay for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, vvhich are vvordes that deſerue poroofe, and
<pb facs="tcp:176516:4"/>a life that will aske amendment: for let them flatter themſelues as fayre as they can, and thinke they do as much as is required of them, when they haue got ten them ſo many liuinges that they may be called of men Rabby, and haue fed themſelues ſo wel that their hearts are ſo fatte as Brawne, yet if their lippes keepe not knowledge, that the people may ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the law of the Lorde at their mouth,<note n="*" place="margin">Mal. 2.8.</note> they haue bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the couenant of Leui, and cauſed many to fall. And let not ſuch as can ſay ſomething thinke they haue knowledge ynough to ſerue all men, for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they knowe howe to gette them many li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings, and to take vpon them the charge of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſoules, that for want of teaching, ſome of them muſt needes goe to the diuell for their ſinnes, they ſhall one day be founde negligent ſhepheards, and<note n="*" place="margin">Ezek. 3.18.</note> the bloud of their ſheepe will be required at their handes. And becauſe the miniſterie is ſo maymed that many of them can skarſe helpe themſelues, and are ſet as candles to giue light vnto others, and yet themſelues are full of darkeneſſe, it ſtandeth euery man vpon to looke to himſelfe, and not to truſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuche as haue no helpe in them. Therefore I vvould wiſhe euery man that doth tender his owne ſaluation, to leaue no meanes vnſought for, that might bring it to paſſe, and to be moſt carefull for the ſame, as that which doth deſerue greateſt labor, if there be any that will ſay they would willingly do it if they knewe vvich vvay to beginne, let<note n="*" place="margin">Iohn. 5.39.</note> them bring themſelues acquainted vvith the vvorde of God vvhich is able to<note n="*" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.16.</note> make them vviſe vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: if they vvill ſay their knowledge is ſmal, and the ſcriptures are hard to be vnderſtoode, let them ſeeke, diligently,<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 7.7.</note> pray hartily, and knocke hard, and
<pb facs="tcp:176516:4"/>the Lorde vvill open the doore of knowledge vnto them, and giue them right hearts of a good vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, if any vvill ſay they haue ſo much to deale in worldly affayres, that they cannot ſpare one hour in the day, to read the vvord of God, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knovv, except all their actions be meaſured by the lyne of Gods vvorde, their labor is loſt, their time ill ſpent, their hope is vaine, their vvroks vnprofitable, and<note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 28.17.</note> all that they take in hande accurſed: if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that thinke themſelues ſo well ſpedde that they need no more teaching, let them learn to put their knowledge in practiſe, in framing their liues accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, leſt when they know<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 12.56.</note> much &amp; doe little, their damnation be the greater: if there be any that vvill ſay there are none ſo vnwiſe, to do that which they know to be vnlawfull, let them know that of that number there are too many, and although the moſt part muſt of neceſſitie confeſſe that there is a God whom they ought to ſerue, yet the diuell doth draw many with great force to liue as thoſe that knovve no God: ſuch is the corruption of mans nature and ſo great are the aſſaultes of our enemie the diuell, that vvhen vve knovv our duetie, and ſee the path way that will lead vs vnto eternall lyfe, yet through the ſuggeſtions of Satan, and the deceitfulneſſe of ſinne, we are drawne to tread the ſteps of death and euerlaſting deſtruction. And ſome there be to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe this their fooly, will defende their life, though neuer ſo vile: and that they may haue the bridle of licentiouſneſſe, to tunne at ran done, though againſt their conſciences, they will not ſpare to call euill good, and good euill, darkneſſe light, and light dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, they that may make a faire ſhew in the worlde, and regard not at all how manifeſtly they lye before
<pb facs="tcp:176516:5"/>the face of almighty God: this fault vvas found in<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 5.4.</note> Ananias Saphira his vvife, for the vvhich they both loſt their liues: and this vvickedneſſe doth ſtill remain amongſt vs, although the puniſhment be not ſo euidently ſeene: of this number are ſo many as know their dutie and lead a life cleane contrary, that knovv lying to bee a faulte, and yet vvill not ſticke to lye for aduantage: that knovv it to be ſinne to ſweare, and yet haue their mouthes full of vayne othes; that know adultery to be abominable in the ſight of God, and yet liue in whordome al the dayes of their life: that knovv murther to be a breach of the lavve, and yet vviſh their brothers throates cut, that they may haue their good: that know coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe to be the roote of all euil, and yet thinke lucre to be godlineſſe: that knovve the rewarde of ſinne to be death, and yet liue in vvickedneſſe al the dayes of their life: theſe men knovve it, yea and vvith all their hearts they knovv it, and vvith ſhame ynough vvill not ſticke to ſay it, and ſhut vp al with tuſhe, God is mercifull, and vvith this cloake they thinke to couer their ſhame, and by that meanes to ſet God beſides his iudgements: but vvhen they ſhall be arraigned before his iudgement ſeate, to aunſwere for the breache of his lavves, I feare me, this cloake of hypocriſie beeing founde on their backes, vvill be taken for the liuery of their maiſter the diuell, vvhom as they haue ſerued in this worlde vvithout any feare of God, ſo ſhal they dwell vvith him for euer in fire euerlaſting, vvhich is prepared for him and his Angels. Theſe are the faultes of our time, and ſuch puniſhments doe follow ſuch ſinnes: and the wickednes of the people is ſo great, that we haue good cauſe to ſay vvith Dauid, that it is<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> time
<pb facs="tcp:176516:5"/>O Lorde, for thee to lay to thine hand. But becauſe theſe thinges are farre from you, vvhich doe ſo ill like of them, that you are an enemye to thoſe that vſe them, you may thinke your ſelf happie and thriſe happie, vvhom God hath deliuered from ſo great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, And for my ſelfe, as I am by duety bounde to do you the beſt ſeruice that I may, and haue recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued more benefites at your handes then euer I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, I can but vviſhe you that vvhich no man can giue you, and pray for that vvhich you may obtaine, that you may ſo ſerue the Lorde of heauen and earth, during the time of your pilgrimage in this ſhorte and tranſitory vvorlde, that vvhen this life ſhall ceaſe, and all vvorldly helpes ſhall fayle you, you may haue God your father, Chriſt your brother, the holy Ghoſt your comforter, the Angels your companions, your inheritance aboue the Heauens, vvith ioyes vnſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable, in a life that ſhall laſt for euer. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worships humble ſeruant. I. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:6"/>
            <head>To the godly Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He eſtate of theſe our dayes is ſo dangerous, the people ſo vngratious, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſin ſo aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, &amp; vertue ſo little ſet by of almoſt al euery where, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it may melt a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hart to meditate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſuch negligence in Magiſtrates, ſuche rebellion in ſubiects, ſuch careleſnes in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers &amp; mothers, and ſuche diſobedience in ſonnes &amp; daughters, that wheras we looke to receiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruits of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, &amp; the bleſſings of heauen powred out vpon vs, according ſo the prouriſe of the Lorde vnto his children: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maruel is great, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the ſun doth not ſkorch vs, the water drowne vs, &amp; the earth gape redy to deuour vs, for our diſobedience and vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfulnes for the ſame. What bleſſings are there which we haue not receiued? and what ſinn is ther but we haue committed? what could a father do more for his owne children, then to keepe them as the apple of his eye? &amp; what tokens of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſterdly impes can there be greater, then to liue as vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> regard not their father? oh howe wel may this complaint of the Prophet be applied vnto vs? y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<note n="*" place="margin">Eſai. 12.</note> Lord hath brought vp children, &amp; they haue done vnfaithfully againſt him, ah ſinfull nation, a people la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb facs="tcp:176516:6"/>with iniquitie, a ſeede of the wicked, ſuch as haue forſaken the Lord, and proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed the holy one of Iſraell to anger, and as the Prophet Oſee ſaid of Iſrael, ſo may it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſayd of England, that<note n="*" place="margin">Oſe. 14.41.</note> ther is no truth, no mercy, no knowledge of god in the land, but ſwearing, lying, &amp; manſlaughter, theft &amp; adultery haue gotten the vpper hand, and one blood guiltines followeth another. Oh y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we knew ſuch an eſtate to be dangerous, &amp; that ſuch ſinnes wil be puniſhed except re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce, what ſhall it profite vs to haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eace vnder our prince, &amp; yet liue as rebels vnto our god? what good ſhal a fruitful cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try bring to a faithles people? What if wee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight liue long in this world, abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elth &amp; proſperity, &amp; in the end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bee ouerta <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en in our ſinne, &amp; rewarded for our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y? what happineſſe is ther in mans eſtate? although he might liue as a prince in this world, and at laſt becom a firebrand in hel: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et thus ſhall it fare with ſuch as feare not God, and great plagues are imminent ouer he Palaces of the wicked, and ſuch as liue vngodly, and it is through the great mercy of our God, and not for deſeruinges, that our eys are not witneſſed that this is true, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut ſince it is the Lordes pleaſure to hee as
<pb facs="tcp:176516:7"/>mercifull vnto vs, as euer he was vnto his own children the people of Iſrael, although our rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s be nothing inferior to theirs, and do with partience &amp; long ſuffering, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure our wickednes, although all the day long he call, and no man doth hear, and ſtill ſtretch out his arme, and no man regards it, yet let vs once looke about our ſelues, &amp; like wiſe children, though long firſt, yet at laſt be come obedient, to ſo bountifull a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And becauſe the very<note n="*" place="margin">Eſai. 1.6.</note> heade is ſicke, and the whole heart is heauy and from the ſole of the foote vnto the crowne of the head there is nothing ſound, but wounds, blains &amp; putrifying ſores, let vs all in time ſeeke ſome remedy for ſo daungerous diſeaſes, that we grow not rotten in our ſinnes, and be paſt cure: and that it fare not with vs as it did with the Iews, that like as the Lord did call vnto<note n="*" place="margin">Zacha. 7.13.</note> them, and they woulde no heare, ſo they cried vnto him and he would not heare: now is it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs as it was with them, nowe doth the Lorde cry vnto vs by the preachers of his word, and call alowd with the ſound of his goſpel. God graunt we neuer ſee the time in which we may ſay for our diſobedience that like as he did call
<pb facs="tcp:176516:7"/>and we woulde not heare, ſo we ſhall cry &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot be hard, And that we may not be found guilty of ſo great ſinnes, and runne in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er of ſo many miſeries, let vs learne to be wiſe in time, and not ſay with the vngrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us ſeruant, my maſter wil be long a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and ſo fall to ſurfferting and drunken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe, and in the ende receiue the wages of vnrighteouſnes, but let vs be penitent with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Publican, that we may intreat y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o haue mercy vpon vs, and that the wrath of his countenaunce, may be far from vs: Let ſin be forſaken, and mercy will be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en, let repentance be found and forgiuenes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s at hande: let amendment of life be a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our true repentance, and heauen &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arth ſhal teſtifie, that the Lord wil be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ifull vnto vs, but if our ſinns remaine ſtil, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f to haue pleaſure in wickedneſſe, be our greateſt delighte, if vertue bée not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but vice hath the higheſt roome: if reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion be onely in our lippes, and the deuill poſſeſſe our hearts: if we be wiſe to do euil, and haue no knowledge to doe well: if to liue as Bulles of <hi>Baſan</hi> vpon the earth, be all we ſéeke for, and the heauenly Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>em we nothing care for: if to haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> muck
<pb facs="tcp:176516:8"/>of this wolrde, we will become bondſlaues to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuil, we ſhalbe ſure to ſerue a maſte that doth pay his ſeruants eternal damna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion for their wages, which wilbe receiued with weeping and gnaſhing of teeth. And although this miſcheife bee a working for the wicked, and great plagues remaine for the vngodly, who are as hard hearted as Pharao, that neuer wil leaue to do euil, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be ouertaken in their ſin: yet let not the faithful feare, but be alwayes glad<note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 44.</note> and reioyce in the Lorde for euer: For he will be their father,<note n="*" place="margin">2. Cor. 6.18.</note> and they ſhall be his ſonnes and daughters, and hee will keepe them as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſignet vpon his finger: let them be contented to abide with patience a little while, and he that wil come<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 10.36.</note> will not tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry long: let them ſuffer a while for Chriſt, and they ſhall reigne with him for euer: let them bee accompted as the abiectes and offſcouring of the people, yet ſhall they one day be found the ſonnes of God, and heires of the kingdome of heauen: let them water their Couche a while with weeping, and the Lorde will once<note n="*" place="margin">Eſa. 15.6. Apoc. 7.17.</note> wipe all teares from their eyes: let them be caſt amongeſt the pottes, and the vileſt places be thought to
<pb facs="tcp:176516:8"/>good for them, yet ſhal they one day be trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as the ſpouſe to méete the brydegrome, and be Citizens of that new Hieruſalem, which ſhall not war old for euer: let them bee as ſheepe<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 8.36.</note> that are dayly ledde to the ſlaughter, yet ſhal they at length be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of their enemies hands, &amp; death ſhal haue no more power ouer them. Let them not faint in the waye, that haue begon to tread the path that leadeth to eternall, life, for their troubles will once haue an ende, and their reward ſhall laſt for euer, there is a day comming when al ſhall be well, and they ſhall ſee Ieruſalem in proſperity, and peace vpon Iſrael. Thus much gentle rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, haue I thought ſufficient for an ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance into the reſt, which I haue written, &amp; through intreaty is put in print, that the ſinnes of our time maye bee knowne, and therby the better auoyded. And as it is the duety of euery man to ſeeke by all meanes poſſibe to bring ſo waightie a matter to paſſe, ſo for mine owne parte, although as vnable as the leaſt, yet as willing as the beſt, haue done what I might, though not as I would, that vertue might be aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and vice ouerthrowne, and do wiſhe it
<pb facs="tcp:176516:9"/>to be read for the end it was written, which was to ſet foorth the glory of God, that our wickednes may be done away, and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life embraced: but if there be any that would ſeeke for painted ſpeech or rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Rhethorike, which is not here to bee found: when they haue opened the booke I woulde wiſhe them to goe no further, for if they ſeeke till they haue reade the whole, they ſhall find in the ende, that they haue but loſt their labour: but if they wold know the truth, here they ſhall finde no lyes, but many thinges that are too true and I wiſh it to be a booke in euery mans hand, that al eſtates might learne ſomewhat, and that the ſounde of it might ring in the cares of all Popiſhe Prieſtes, couetous Miniſters, and vnlearned Paſtors, that when they ſée as in a glaſſe their ſinnes laid before them, their duetie ſhewed them, and in the ende, and example of repentance: they may learne of the beſt, and forſake the worſt, that God in them may be glorified, and them ſelues in Chriſt ſanctified.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Farewell gentle Reader, I pray thee reade through the booke before thou iudge of it.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:9"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>A Dialogue betweene a</hi> vertuous gentleman, and a Popiſh <hi>Priest, riding on the</hi> way.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gentleman.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou are well ouertake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten maſter Parſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon,</speaker>
               <p>You are welcome gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Parſon, how farre ride you this way?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Truly ſir, I haue fourty miles to go, and I meane not (by Gods grace) to ſtope before I come to my iourneis end.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>And I muſt ride as far, an almoſt ſo much farther, and I am glad that it is my chance to fall into ſo good company as a man of your coat, for they are (or ſhould be all) ſuch as the company where they are preſent ſhould be the better for: &amp; I know that with the<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal.</note> holy, men ſhalbe holy, with
<pb facs="tcp:176516:10"/>the perfect, me ſhall be perfect, with the cleane men ſhalbe cleane, and with the fro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward, men ſhall learne frowardneſſe: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to come in company wher a man may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e beſt taught, is to haue the greateſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that in this world may be founde, and I pray you ſir what is your name?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>The name that was giuen me in my baptiſme, is Iohn,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
               <p>And I beſeech you (maſter parſon) If I may be ſo bold to aſke what is youre ſirname?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Truely gentleman, my ſirname is bad (ſauing that I know the name doeth neuer make nor mar the man) I would be ſo, to ſhewe you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
               <p>What euer be your name, you need feare, no ſhame thereof, for as it is not your good name that coulde profite you, if your life be euill: ſo ſhal not your bad name hurt you, if your life be good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>To tell you my name, and to ſaye the troth, it is <hi>Neuer be good.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What? maſter <hi>Neuer be good?</hi> I know many worſhipfull gentlemen of that name, and therefore you neede not to diſdaine the name.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:10"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>In deede there are many gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of that name, and I my ſelfe am a gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tleman borne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Are you ſo? it is no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon thing to ſee a gentlemans ſonne to take vppon him the miniſterye, for they will chuſe rather ſome faculty, whereby they may liue at eaſe, then betake themſelues to the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry, which is a painfull vocation being vſed as it ought.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Truely you ſay the trothe, it is a new thing to ſee gentlemens ſonnes giuen to the miniſtrie, and I promiſe you it was neuer my deſire to take vpon me that func<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but if you will giue me leaue, I will ſhewe you howe I came to it, and by what meanes I did attaine to my liuing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, I praye you (maiſter Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) ſay on, let me hear the whole diſcourſe therrof, it will cauſe our long iourney to ſeeme much the ſhorter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>The troth is, my father hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie children, &amp; of them all I was the yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt, and for his eldeſt ſonnes he had great care to bring them vp in learning, ſome at the vniuerſitie, and ſome at the Innes of the Courte: but I beeing the yongeſt of
<pb facs="tcp:176516:11"/>them all, was kept at home, to be my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wanton, and I was ſo trained vp in pleaſure, and had in my yong yeeres ſo much mine owne deſire, that when I came to riper age, my parentes, which in my youth had kept me at home to ſerue their turne, coulde not by any meanes perſwade me to goe from them, althoughe it mighte haue beene the better for me: but as they had begun to keepe me at home? and tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned mee vp in wantonnes, ſo I meant al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to continue at home, and leade my life in lewdneſſe: and my father at length perceiuing where vnto I was inclined, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing alwayes a deſire that I ſhoulde doe well, was ſory to ſee me ſo ill diſpoſed, and behelde the ſame to his great griefe: and did vſe as many means as he might, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graffe in me ſome goodneſſe: but he ſeeing that I was made of ſuch mettall, that no goodnes would hang about mee, (and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to much experience thereof) it had all moſt coſt him his life, to ſe al the reſt of his ſonnes brought vp to his contentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſome Lawyers, and ſome Courtiers, and all had ſomewhat, and I being as deare his childe as the reſt of my brethren, he was ſory that
<pb facs="tcp:176516:11"/>I had not ſoed ſo well as they had done, &amp; when he wel perceiued, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſighing could not ſalue this matter, nor his thought taken (which did hurt him ſelfe) could do me any good, although full ſore againſt his will, when he ſaw I was paſte all hope of any goodneſſe, had no ſhift for me but to make me a miniſter, and when I was a miniſter it was not long before I had a benefice (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I payed well for him) and when I was once mine owne man, and had gotten my ſelfe aforehand, it ws not long before I had another, and hauing enioyed theſe <hi>2.</hi> benefices, <hi>3</hi> or <hi>4.</hi> yeeres, I was gotten in ſuch credite amongſt the gentlemen of our countrey, what by houſe keeping, &amp; what by good felowſhip, that there was not a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice that ſhould lightly fall in that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, but I ſhoulde be heard for my money before another: ſo that now I thanke God &amp; good friends, I haue <hi>3.</hi> benefices whiche bee worth me <hi>3.</hi> hundred good markes by the yere, and although I be no lawyer nor Courtier, with the reſt of my brethren, yet I dare bè bold to ſay, I liue as merry at my hearts caſe as the proudeſt of them all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen,</speaker>
               <p>Were theſe the ſteppes whereby
<pb facs="tcp:176516:12"/>you came to ſuch promotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? I perceiue you are not the man that I took you for, nor yet the man that you ſhoulde bee: are you but one miniſter and haue you ſo many benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? and hauing ſo many? haue you gotten them all by ſimonie? beleeue mee, beleeue me (maſter Parſon) I am ſorie to heare ſo ill of you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſir, is there ſuche hurt in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſo many benefices? and it is not lawfull to come by them as a man maye haue them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Truely I will tell you what I thinke, and to ſhewe you may iudgement in matter (to be plane with you) I eſteeme it to be ſtarknaked naughte, for the buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of your benefices howe tollerable it is, you maye knowe it to bee as lawfull for a miniſter to buy a benefice, as it is for the Patron to ſell that whiche is none of his owne: and it is as lawfull for the Patron to ſell a benefice, as it was for<note n="*" place="margin">Acts. 8.18.</note> Simon Magus to obteine the giftes of the holye Ghoſt for monie, and becauſe both Patron and Prieſt are gyltie of the ſame, I would wiſhe them to repent of this their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, vnleſſe them ſelues with their monie
<pb facs="tcp:176516:12"/>do periſh together.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What then? would you not haue a miniſter to haue a benefice before it be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him freely? ſo hee may goe without a benefice a good while.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>I woulde not haue the miniſterye to be corrupted with ſuch faultes, of al the men in the worlde, for it becometh them as they oughte to teache the trueth vnto their flocke, ſo they<note n="*" place="margin">1. Pet. 5.2.</note> are to bee an example vnto them of good liuing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>But (by your leaue Syr) before you condemne the matter, you muſt prooue it to be a fault.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Why? doe you not acknowledge your fault? in ſo doing you make the faulte greater: for, to ſinne and not to be ſorye for ſinne, is to heape ſinne vpon<note n="*" place="margin">Eccle. 23.11.</note> ſinne, and in the end to reape the reward of iniquitie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>But I pray you Syr, doe you think there is ſuch a fault in buying of benefices, as you ſpeake of? and that it is any offence againſt God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Truely I am perſwaded that if Chriſt were now amongſt vs (as he was ſometime amongſt the Iewes) and did ſee the marchandize that is made of benefices
<pb facs="tcp:176516:13"/>now a days, he that could then ſo ill like of<note n="*" place="margin">Matt. 21.12.</note> buying and ſelling in the churche, would woorſe like of buying and ſelling of the churche, and therfore I think they that buy and ſell benefices doe better deſerue a whip to be ſcourged out of the churche, then to have any thing at all to doe concorning the Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Me thinkes you take the matter very hardly, for truely I am of this mind, that if a man buy a bencefice, when the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is once tolde, the benefice is cleane ſold, and then it is lawful for the miniſter to vſe it as his owne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>And I thinke it is more lawfull for you to vſe it as your owne when you once haue it, then it is to pay for it, when it is in your choyſe to leaue it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>And are you of the ſame minde of hauing many benefices, that it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for one man to haue more then one?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke it to be as lawfull for you to haue <hi>3.</hi> benefices, as it is for me to haue <hi>3.</hi> wiues, and as the one by the law of man is vnlawfull, ſo are they both in the ſight of God moſt abhominable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you Syr ſhewe me ſome
<pb facs="tcp:176516:13"/>reaſon for theſe matters, I neuer hard man ſo diſlike with theſe thinges (as you doe) before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe bee the reaſons that cauſe me to thinke that the hauing of more then one benefice for one man to bee vnlawfull. Firſt becauſe it is not lawfull for one man to haue more then one man can diſcharge: ſecondly that the miniſter ſhoulde not the ſo fed with the vaine deſires of this corrupte worlde, that it mighte drawe him from the loue of the worlde to come: for as they feede them ſelues, ſo they feede others, and ſuch meate as they receiue into their owne bellies, the breth thereof they blowe vppon their whole pariſhioners, &amp; being perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that it is lawfull for themſelues, to liue as hogges in a Stye, connot teach their flocke any other doctrine then to feede the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues as the Oxe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is fed to the flaughter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, I pray you Syr (ſauing your tale) cannot one man diſcharge three bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>No, I muſte tell you nowe, as I tolde you before, I knowe it, and I woulde wiſh you to remember it, that it is not law full for one man to haue more then one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176516:14"/>can diſcharge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>That is wel ſaid, I wil ſay ſo too, &amp; of this matter I can ſpeake by experience, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one man may wel diſcharge thrée benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for I my ſelfe haue had three benefices almoſt theſe twenty yeres, and (I thanke God) I know not the man that can aſke a penny of me for the diſcharge of the ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Oh (maſter parſon) I praye you miſtake me not, I meane not but you may agree with the world for greater matters then theſe, but when you haue diſcharged your ſelf of this world, &amp; this world ſhalbe diſcharged of you, then haue you the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſte account of all to reckon for, for when you are deade and leuiled all youre ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countes with man, then ſhall you bee ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned before<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 9.27.20.24.12.</note> te iudgemente ſeate of God, there to aunſwére to ſuch thinges as ſhalbe layd to your charge, and if you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not then anſwer for your ſelf, no man ſhall be aloud to ſpeak for your if you be deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded how you entred into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſtery, what will you ſay, your father did compell you? ſo you &amp; your Father for ſimning together ſhal without repentance be deſtroied for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: if you be demanded how you came by your benefices, wil you ſay, you haue paid
<pb facs="tcp:176516:14"/>ſufficiently for them, and your Patrons and you did agree wel ynough? ſo you may prooue your ſelfe well friended amongſt men, and be vtterly caſt out of the fauoure of God: if you be demanded howe you haue liued, will you ſay you haue beene a good fellowe, and haue fed youre Pariſhioners with the fruites of their owne handes? ſo you may haue heauen and earth to beare witnes againſt you, for liuing by the ſwet of other mens brows: if you be aſked when you haue fed their bodies, how you haue fed their ſouls, if you ſaid ſo manie benefices, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> you could not be reſident on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al at once, &amp; therefore doe what you could, you coulde not do as you ſhould, you ſhall be ſure to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiue the reward of an vnprofitable ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Yea: but ſir I ſay not ſo, neither do I thinke, but that I doe diſcharge my <hi>3.</hi> benefices as well as if I had but one, for becauſe I cannot my ſelfe be in all places at all times: I haue two miniſters that do ſee as good order in my other <hi>2.</hi> benefices, as if I were there my ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>I beleeue you (Maſter Parſon) that the order of your miniſters, and your owne, is much like: but doe you thinke to
<pb facs="tcp:176516:15"/>doe your dutie by an attorney? ſo you may chaunce to go to heauen by an attorney.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>You are the ſtraungeſt gentleman that euer I talked withall, do you find ſuch faulte in me, for hauing <hi>3.</hi> benefices, and theſe <hi>3.</hi> lie ſomewhat rounde togeather? what if I can tell you of one man that hath <hi>4.</hi> benefices, and euery of them is fourſcore miles a ſunder: howe thinke ye, may hee ſupplie ſo many, &amp; beeing ſo farre one from the other?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke hee maye better ſupplie theſe <hi>4.</hi> then you do your <hi>3,</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What doe you thinke ſo? I woulde fain know how ſo vnlikely a matter might be brought to paſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Thus in my iudgement it might very well be done: firſt, if he were hanged, then if vpon euery of his foure pariſh chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches were hanged one of his four quarters, ſo ſhoulde all his pariſhioners bee ſure, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to haue ſome part of their parſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par</speaker>
               <p>Ah, I perceiue you are a merie Gentleman, and diſpoſed to leſt, therefore and you ſay the worde (by my faith) let vs haue a little merrie talke another while.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:15"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What (maſter Parſon) doe you ſweare?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Oh I cry you mercy ſir, can you not abide ſwearing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, cry God mercie, for it is him that you haue offended and not me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Why, is there ſuche an offence in ſwearing one little othe, as by my faith?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Yea no doubt, although the othe ſeeme little in your eies, yet the offence is great in the ſight of God: and I maruaile that you which haue taken vpon you to be a teacher, are now to learn that leſſon: ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore I woulde wiſhe you, either learne to leaue your ſwearing, or leaue your name of teaching, for commonly ſuche a maſter, ſuch ſchollers, and where the blind lead the blinds, they both fall into the dike.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Me thinkes you take vppon you to be maſter controller, and I thinke you haue (ſince our firſt talke) ſpoken more then you can prooue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>No, (maſter parſon) I meane not to Controle you, but I ſeeke by all meanes to amend you, and as for that which I haue ſaide, or doe meane to ſaie, I doubt not, but I am able to auouch it by the word of God
<pb facs="tcp:176516:16"/>and if you thinke that you can diſproue me and proue that you ſaye by the ſcripture, I am contented to be taught of you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Naye I promiſe you I haue no ſcripture</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What haue you no ſcripture? then you are woorſe then the Diuell, for he had ſome ſcripture, when he<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 4.6.</note> tempted Chriſte he was not without ſcripture: but you ſay you haue none, and therfore in that reſpect you are inferiour to the diuell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Truely Gentleman you make but a homely compariſon, but I am contented you ſhal ſay your pleaſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>And you are a very homely mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, that you ſhame not to ſay you haue no knowledge in the ſcripture. What a pitiful thinge is this? that you whiche are in the roome of a maſter, and haue manie ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers to teache and ſee well brought vp, or elſe a hard an account to make: that you are altogeather without knowledge. You take it vpon you to be on of them that will giue light (as a randell) to them that ſit in darkeneſſe, and are placed in Moſes chaire to ſhew the law of the Lorde vnto his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: but I perceiue you may goe amongſte
<pb facs="tcp:176516:16"/>the number of thoſe ſhepheards whom the<note n="*" place="margin">Eſai. 56.16.</note>Prophet complaineth of, that are altogea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without vnderſtading, that are blind that are dumbe dogges and cannot barke. For I ſee well you are no preacher of the word.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>No in deed, it was neuer my brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging vp.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What, can you ſay nothing? then you maye goe learne of <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe, for he<note n="*" place="margin">Nom. 22.27.</note> could ſaie ſomewhat, and feare before the Angel of the Lorde, but you can ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, nor fear the iudgements of God due for ſo great a ſin: (although you are in ſuch eſtimation that you are called maſter par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) yet you are worſe then <hi>Blaaams</hi> Aſſe in condition.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke I am ſo not bad as you make me, for I can read the word vnto the people, and is not that ſufficient?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>No, that will not ſuffice, for one of your calling muſt not onely read the word, but be able to expound the ſame, and ſuche thinges as are harde to be vnderſtoode, to make plaine vnto the people, for faith com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by hearing,<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 10.14.</note> and hearing by the word of God, and howe ſhall they heare without
<pb facs="tcp:176516:17"/>a Preacher, and Solomon ſayth, where<note n="*" place="margin">Pro. 11.14.</note> Gods worde is not preached, the people goe to decay: ſo that you may now ſee (if you be not ſtarke blind) how farre you are out of the way, and how vnfitte you are to haue the charge ouer ſoules, which are vnable to preach, and cannot vſe that ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary meanes to ſaue the people, which is ordeined to bring them vnto faluation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I perceiue you are a Puritant out right, you are one of theſe new me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> would haue nothing but preaching, it was neuer merry world ſince y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſect came firſt amongſt vs: for I dare be hold to ſay, that there was more good fellowſhip in the old time, and all thinges were better cheape when wee had little preaching or none at all, and a man might haue more for a peny, then he can haue now for a groat, therfore I think we haue now ſo much preaching that wee are the worſe for it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What (maſter parſon) are you of that minde? that the preaching of the word of God (which is the greateſt bleſſing that we haue amongſt vs) is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe of our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happines? Oh in any wiſe thinke not ſo: for the vngodly people in the time of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb facs="tcp:176516:17"/>
                  <hi>Ieremie,</hi> were of the ſame wicked o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, and tolde him the like tale, that when they did<note n="*" place="margin">Iere. 44.17.</note> ſeruice vnto the Queene of Heauen, they were in proſperity, and had all things plemie: but when they did leaue ſuch vngodly behauiour, all thinges went wrong with them, and their eſtate was vn happy, and therefore they though that to ſerue God, was the cauſe of their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes: but the Prophet tolde them, as I may tel you, that<note n="*" place="margin">Iere. 44.22.</note> our ſinnes are the cauſe of our troubles, and we are puniſhed for not walking in the waies of the Lord. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (maſter parſon) you are farre deceiued to thinke that the preaching of the Goſpell doth hurt the people, and now I well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that there is not that in you, which I thought to haue found in a man of your cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling, therefore to diſcharge mine owne du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and for the loue I beare vnto the truth, I (will according to my ſmall knowledge) ſhew you what is the duetie of true ſheepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heardes, of the which number I know you would goe for one. Firſt it is ſayde in the propheſie of <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> that the<note n="*" place="margin">Ezek. 33.7.</note> ſhephard is made a watch man ouer his flocke, to giue them warning from the lorde, and if they
<pb facs="tcp:176516:18"/>ſinne, and he ſhew them not of it, that then they ſhall dye in their ſinnes, &amp; their bloud ſhall be requyred at the paſtors handes: but if hee giue them warning and thye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend not, they ſhall die in their ſinnes, but the miniſter hath ſaued his own ſoule, ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther Prophet ſaith, that the Prieſts lippes ſhoulde<note n="*" place="margin">Mal. 2.7.</note> keepe ſure knowledge, that the people may ſeek the law at his mouth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee is the meſſenger of the Lorde of Hoſtes. And the Apoſtle Paule ſayth: that a miniſter<note n="*" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.2.</note> muſt be baameleſſe, watching, ſober, apt to teach, not greedy of filthy lucre holding the miſtery of faith in pure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and Peter agreeing with him, would haue them to feed<note n="*" place="margin">3. Pet. 5.2.</note> their flocke, not as though they were Lords ouer their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners, but that they giue a good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſample vnto them of wel doing, and that of good will, and Paule (in another place) would haue them to be inſtant, in<note n="*" place="margin">2. Tim. 4.2.</note> ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, and no time exempted wherein they may be doing good. This is your duetie, and if this be in you, then doe you play the part of a wiſe ſeruant, whom his maſter, when hee commeth ſhall finde wel doing: but if this be ſarr from you, and
<pb facs="tcp:176516:18"/>the name of ſhepheard be only to be found, you are a Wolfe, cloathed in a Sheepes ſkinne, and ſhall haue your portion with the vngodly, in that lake of fire and Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, which ſhall not bee quenched for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Truely ſir, it is a harde matter to finde all this in one man, and although I haue not this in me, yet I truſt I ſhal haue no parte in that fierie lake whereof you ſpeake, nor there is no ſuch daunger in the matter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>That you may not thinke it to be an vntruth, or any inuention of mine own making, marke what the ſcripture ſayth, which cannot lye. Wo<note n="*" place="margin">Iere. 48.10.</note> be vnto him that doth the worke of the Lord negligently A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,<note n="*" place="margin">Ezek. 34.2.</note> Wo be vnto the Shepheardes that feed themſelues, ſhoulde not a Shepheard feede his flocke? Paule cryed<note n="*" place="margin">Cor. 9.16.</note> Wo vnto him ſelfe if hee preache not the Goſpell, and you ſhall one day cry, Wo vnto your ſelfe if you preache not the Goſpel,<note n="*" place="margin">Ezeck. 23.3.</note> Wo vnto the fooliſhe Prophetes that followe their owne braines.<note n="*" place="margin">Iere. 23.1.</note> Wo vnto the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heardes, that deſtroy and ſcatter my flocke (ſaith the Lorde) and ſo thruſte them out
<pb facs="tcp:176516:19"/>that they once looke not vppon them: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will I one day viſite the wickednes of their vaine imaginations, here you haue heard a great many of Woes, and al theſe and a great many more, ſhall fall on you, if in time you ſeeke not ſome meanes to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>In deede Syr, I muſt needes ſaye you haue told me of many woes, and yet I truſt what ſo euer you ſay, there ſhal none of them light on me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Truely I haue ſayde nothing of my ſelfe, but that which I haue tolde you are the reportes of other men, which vſed not to lye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>And doe you thinke in deede, that all theſe woes are pronounced againſt ſuch miniſters as preach not the Goſpell, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> if they continue in that ſtate, they ſhal haue them in their portion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you (maſter Parſon) let me firſt aſke you this queſtion: do you thinke that the Prophets and Apoſtles haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken any thing in vaine?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I doe not thinke ſo, but peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it may be true.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Nay I will tell you, without per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture,
<pb facs="tcp:176516:19"/>that which they haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſo true,<note n="*" place="margin">Math. 5.18.</note> that heauen and earth ſhal fal, before that one iot that they haue ſaid ſhal periſh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I doe not deny but that the worde of God muſt needes ſtand, but if you will ſo conſter the ſcriptures, that all miniſters that preach not the Goſpell ſhall be cryed Woe vnto, you will make a mad peece of worke, and ſende moſt of the miniſters in theſe dayes to the deuil.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>I go not about to ſend any man to the deuill, but I doe what in me lieth to drawe them vnto God: and therefore I would wiſh you and your fellowes, to looke to this geare in time, vnleſſe you repent hereafter when it will bee too late, for if your dueties be neglected, and this great charge can not be anſweared when it ſhall be examined, you and your fellowes ſhal be ſure to ſmart for it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Why? what would you haue me to do? that you find ſuch fault in vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Truly I would wiſh you to deale no longer in the matter you haue taken vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, and are not able to go throgh with it, out repent for that which is paſt, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend that is to come, and let it not be long
<pb facs="tcp:176516:20"/>a doing: but take the councell of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet that would haue vs to<note n="*" place="margin">Eſay. 55.6.</note> ſeek the Lord while he may be found, and call vppon him while he may be heard, let the vngodly ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſaith he) forſake his owne waies, and the wicked his vain imaginations, and return vnto the Lorde, ſo ſhall he be mercifull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and vnto our God, for he is ready to forgiue. Oh refuſe not this offer (ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter parſon) as you loue your owne ſoule, for if you take it not while you may haue it hereafter you may chance to ſeeke it with teares and goe without it, for nowe is the acceptable time, and euery tree that bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not foorth good fruite, the<note n="*" place="margin">Math. 13.10.</note> axe is layd to his roote, that it may be cut downe and caſt into the fire: therefore be not leaue off from ſinn, which without ſhame you haue greedily committed, be no longer amongſt the number of thoſs whome <hi>Paul</hi> ſpcaketh of, that they are the enemies of the<note n="*" place="margin">Phi. 3.10.</note> croſſe of Chriſte, whoſe end is damnation, whoſe God is their belly, &amp; glory to their ſhame, which are worldly minded, let no longer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of this world, draw you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the loue of God: but<note n="*" place="margin">Iam 4.7.</note> draw neere vnto him, and he wil
<pb facs="tcp:176516:20"/>drawe neere vnto you: reſiſt the deuill and hee will fly from you, purge your handes, and clenſe your heart, &amp; humble your ſelfe in the ſight of the Lorde, and hee ſhall lift you vp. Let the ſame mind be in you which was in <hi>Moſes,</hi> who when hee was great,<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 11.2.</note> refuſed to be called the ſonne of <hi>Pharaobs</hi> daughter, and choſe rather to ſuffer aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity with the children of God, then to enioy the pleaſures of ſinne for a ſeaſon: eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the rebuke of Chriſte more riches, then al the treaſure of Egypt. And with Sainte <hi>Paul</hi> ſaye that you<note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 3.8.</note> account al the world but dung that you may win Chriſt, &amp; giue ouer your liuings, vnlawfully poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, in this ſhort and tranſitory world, that you may liue for euer in the world to come.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What do you mean by al this talk, that I ſhuld giue ouer my benefices? ſo you may chaunce to beginne a peece of worke which you ſhal neuer finiſh, for I had as leeue looſe my life as looſe my liuing, and I haue not had them this long, to forgo the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at laſt, therefore gentleman, I ſhal deſirs you to haue me excuſsd for this matter, and I wil here you in any thing ſaue this: ther is no man ſo vnwiſe I thinke, to forſake
<pb facs="tcp:176516:21"/>his liuing and become a begger, when it is in his choiſe to vſe it at his pleaſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>In deed (maſter Parſon) I thinke few men be ſo wiſe, to doe that which may be beſt for them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What, doe you account that wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? I am ſure there are many wiſe men of the miniſterie, as you know as well as I, that haue more liuings then I haue, and yet I thinke you can not tel me of one that doth loue the Goſpell ſo wel, that he would depart with any of his benefices, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge his conſcience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>In deed (as you ſay) a man ſhall hardly finde one amongeſt ſo many double beneficed men, that will preferre the truth, before their benefices, or loue the Lord bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then them ſelues: but ſuch deſerue not the name of wiſe men, for if their be any wiſdome in them, it is ſuch as the prophet ſpeaketh of, that<note n="*" place="margin">Iere. 4.22.</note> are wiſe to doe euill, but to doe well they haue no knowledge, and if ſcripture will no ſerue to perſwade you, yet let me ſee what reaſon may mooue you: do you think that our Lord Chriſt, who is heire of heauen and earth, whoſe ſeruantes we will ſay we are, &amp; vnder whoſe banner
<pb facs="tcp:176516:21"/>we will ſay we fight: if he then being our maſter, and<note n="*" place="margin">Phi. 4.21.</note> thought it no robberie to bee equall with God, and yet made him ſelfe of no reputation, and refuſed notto take vpon him the ſhape of a ſeruaunt, and to humble himſelfe vnto the death of the croſſe for our ſakes, that we by his example, might learn for his great loue, to loue him againe, and was taught obedience by the thinges that he ſuffered, to ſubmit himſelf to his fathers will, and was contented for our ſakes to beare this heauy burden, before hee entred into his glory: and do you thinke it reaſon that a gret many of you, which are drawn from the Carts taile and ſet with Princes, that you ſhall mocke him with the name of ſeruaunts, and yet liue as maſter, and ſay you fight vnder his banner, and ſtrike the ſtroke with his enemies, &amp; in the end be ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>counted as his brethren, &amp; eate and drinke in his kingdome? no, no, (maſter Parſon) deceiue not your ſelfe,<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 6.7.</note> he will not be moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, they are thoſe that<note n="*" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.12.</note> ſuffer with him, and ſuch as deny him, he will deny them: or thinke you that there is any new way to heauen, better then Chriſte him ſelfe hath found? no, doubt you not, if theer had beene
<pb facs="tcp:176516:22"/>any way eaſier, then through many tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations to enter into heauen, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father wold haue reuealed it to his onely begotten ſon. Therefore (maſter Parſon) ſeeing the caſe ſtandeth as it doth, I maruaile that before you meant to be a builder in this woorke, you had not firſt made your account what it would haue coſt you, for it is ſuch a péece of worke as wil not be done without great charge, for experience doth teach vs, that it hath coſte many a man all that they haue had, yea and their liues alſo, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they might be found painfull labourers in ſo ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a building.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Truely Gentleman, I muſt needs confeſſe that the ſcripture is true, and your reaſons are verye good, and if I thought there were no other ſence to bee gathered out of the ſcripture, then you haue ſhewed me, I might chance to do that which ſome times I neuer thought to haue done: but although there be many places that threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten puniſhment to the greeuous offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, yet I know there are ſome that teach vs: that God is mercifull: and I for my part doe not meane to come to heauen by mine owne deſertes, but I do only hope of
<pb facs="tcp:176516:22"/>the mercy of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>To truſt in Gods mercy you doe wel, for if you ſhould think to come to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by your own merites, you ſhould ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be deceiued, but ſo to hope of his mercy as thoſe that care not for it, is to truſt to a broken ſtaffe, and in the ende to be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Tuſhe I know God is merciful, and ſome there be (and that a great many) that ſhal taſt of his mercy, and why ſhold not I be one of them, as ſoone as an other?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>But (maſter Parſon) in any wiſe deceiue not your ſelfe, but take the counſel of the wiſe man, which ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">Eccle. 5.6.</note> ſay not tuſh the Lorde is mercifull, he ſhall forgiue me my ſinnes, by they neuer ſo many, for as he is mercifull, ſo departeth wrath from him, &amp; in the time of vengeance he ſhal deſtroy thee: but becauſe it is true, that God is mercifull, and ſome there be that ſhall taſt of his mercie, and you are one of them that woulde faine taſt of his mercie, I will tell you how you maie get it, and alſo how you ſhal know when ſhe is ſure to haue it. The prophet Eſay ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">Eſay. 55.7.</note> Let the vngodly man forſake his owne waies, and the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb facs="tcp:176516:23"/>his owne imaginations, and turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vnto the Lorde, ſo ſhall he be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto him: ſo by this you may ſee, that the way to haue Gods mercy, is to forſake your ſinne, and when you find from the bot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tome of your heart, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> you do loth your wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe and hate your ſinnes as the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt enemies you haue, and leaue them as thinges daungerous to bee had in keeping: when you finde this in you, be ſure that the mercy of the Lorde, is not farre from you, but if a man will not turne, he will whette<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 7.13.</note> his ſworde, and bend his bowe, to the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting down and vtter deſtruction of the wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked and vngodly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>And muſt I needes put away my benefices (thinke you) before I am like to obteine the mercy of God, and atteine to his heauenly kingdome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Truly (Maſter Parſon) I will tell you,<note n="*" place="margin">Math. 7.14.</note> the way to heauen is very ſtraite: and it will be a harde matter, for one man with three benefices to paſſe throughe ſo narrowe a place: therefore if you will bee ſure to come thither your ſelfe, I woulde wiſh you to leaue youre benefices behinde you.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:23"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Why? do you think y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I meant to carry my benefices with me? ther is no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo vnwiſe (I thinke) but knoweth he ſhall leaue al things behind him, when he dieth</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>But if you bee not diſcharged of them while you may, you ſhall bee ſure to be troubled with them, when you wil wiſh that you had neuer ſeene them, when the bloude of your ſheepe ſhall be required at your handes, their ſinnes will lie ſo heauy on your backe, that when you are come to the gate ready to enter into heauen (I feare me) they will plucke you downe as farre as the bottomles pit of hel: therefore if you will follow the counſel of him that wiſheth you well, now ſo deal with the worlde, that hereafter you repent not your bargin: and<note n="*" place="margin">Math. 5.2.</note> agree with your aduerſary while you are in the way, leaſt he deliuer you vnto the iudge, and the iudge deliuer you vnto the Gailor, and he caſt you into priſon, &amp; thence not to come out, till you haue made good the vtmoſte farthing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>For your good counſel I moſt hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely thanke you, and follow it I would if I thought if beſt for me, the pathes that lead to heauen I would fain tread, and the way
<pb facs="tcp:176516:24"/>to hell I wold willingly auoid, for I know that theſe places, the one from the other do ſo farr differ, that to know the way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen is onely my deſire, and that I might be ſure not to miſſe the waie, I coulde be contented to depart with one of my benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (with all my hart) ſo that I might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the reſt quietlie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>I am glad that you are come one ſtep lower, and it putteth me in hope y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> you will not ſtick to take a little more paine in this vile and tranſitorie world, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> you may reſt for euer in the world to come, and that this world may not deceiue you, conſider it as it is, and think no better of it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it doth deſerue, &amp; loue it no dearer then you would your enemie: for the Apoſtle ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">1. Iohn. 2.15.</note> if we loue the world or the things in the world, the loue of God is not in vs: and if you wil ſay you<note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 14.2.4.</note> loue God and keepe not his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandementes, you will prooue your ſelfe a liar, &amp; there is no truth in you. Know ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> this world is vaine, and al worldlie things are vanitie, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righteouſnes is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect bleſſednes, and to know God in truth, is the cheefeſt felicitie: and to put away confidence in man, or any worldly helpe, is
<pb facs="tcp:176516:24"/>to truſt to a broken ſtaffe, which in thende will deceiue you: thinke no fréedome ſo to be deſired as the ſeruice of God, &amp; to know that better it is for you to be Chriſts Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin without a benefice, then to haue all the liuinges in the worlde, and bee out of his ſeruice, and thinke it not inough to depart with one benefice and keepe two in your hand, but if you may be vnburdened of that which you cannot diſcharge, and haue par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for your former ſinnes committed, ſay you are well vſed and finne no more: and Chriſte teacheth vs, that he that wil be his diſciple,<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 16.2.</note> muſt deny himſelfe, and take vp his croſſe and follow him. Now if I ſhould counſel you to keepe any thing that might hurt you or hinder Gods glory, I ſhoulde go beyond my commiſſion, and commit ſin with you: therefore to tel you the troth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you are an vnpreaching Prelate, and vnmeet for that office, I would wiſh you to giue ouer the function you haue no ſkill-of, and leaue al your benefices, as things that perteine not vnto you. Let not ſo many ſoules periſhe, through one mans negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, but haue a care of your ſelfe as well as of them, &amp; flatter not your ſelfe any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
<pb facs="tcp:176516:25"/>leaſt you &amp; your flock periſh togeather: let ſuche haue your roome that can teache them better, and let ſuch ſhere the ſheepe as can feede the flocke, that you may ſaue your ſelfe and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, let not worldly perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions worke you deſtruction, but let ſuch flatterers goe for lyers, that will tell you, you are vnwiſe if you ſo doe, you ſhall looſe your credite, you friends wil faile you, no man wil regard you, let theſe and ſuch like tales goe for chaffe, that is blowne awaye with the winde, and whoſe ſubſtaunce will ſoone haue an ende, for if the Lorde will be ſerued, and his iudgement executed for ſo great a ſinne, al the world cannot pay your ranſome, neither ſhall any man be able to ſet you free. Therfore in this matter deale wiſely for your ſelfe, for it is your ſelfe that ſhall ſtand to the ſtake for the whole: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part with this vngodly promotion, which this wicked worlde hath brought you, and you ſhall haue treaſure in heauen, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſo that you are not able to take vppon you the charge of ſoules, withoute the deſtruction of your ſelfe and them, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge your ſelfe quite of ſo great a daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and keepe not a benefice for feare of
<pb facs="tcp:176516:25"/>diſpleaſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What, wil you not haue me keepe one benefice? then you deale more hardly with mee then I thought you woulde: but there ſhal be no more adoe of the matter, I will kepe my ſelfe as I am, and therefore in vſing theſe perſwaſions, you doe but looſe your labour, the charge is mine, and I one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhall auſwere for it, therefore I woulde wiſh you to looke to your ſelfe, and take no farther care for me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What, are you nowe come to this paſſe? and is this the thanke that for my good will I ſhall receiue? I was in good hope when you were once running, you would not haue ſtaied before you had come to the goale: but oh howe true is that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nowe fulfilled in you, which was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſo long agone? that<note n="*" place="margin">2. Pet. 2.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> the dogge is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to his old vomite againe, &amp; the ſow that was waſhed, to her wallowing in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mire: Oh couetouſnes, couetouſnes, howe well may it be called the roote<note n="*" place="margin">1 Tim. 10.6.</note> of all euil? that ſendeth ſo many ſoules headlong to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuel.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What, you are farre deceiued (gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman) do you thinke that couetouſnes is in mee, no, I abhorre it with al my heart,
<pb facs="tcp:176516:26"/>and loue of monie is farre from me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What are you not couetous: I pray you, what did then moue you to take 3. benefices? when as one of them is liuing ſufficient for you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I perceiue you knowe not what you ſay, for I tel you troth, I can not liue with one benefice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>No? I praye you what is one of your benefices (that doth yeelde you leaſte) worth you by the yeere?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke it bee woorth me, a fortie or fifie pounds.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>And I pray you what do you giue vnto your Curate by the yeare, that doeth ſerue your benefice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I giue him ten pound by the yere.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>And why can you not liue with fourty or fiftie pounds by the year? as well as your Curate that hath but ten pounde by the yeare?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I ſee well (Gentleman) you take all things at the worſt, but I will tell you, and not lye vnto you, wherfore one benefice would not content mee, and ſo ſmall a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing will not ſatiſfie me, I did conſider my calling, how that I was a gentleman, and
<pb facs="tcp:176516:26"/>therefore I thought it not ynough for mee to liue as the common ſorte doe, which are but plaine fellowes of the country, and I knew no way how to make any difference, but onlie by procuring my ſelf ſuch liuings as might mainteine me like a gentleman, and being once a miniſter, you knowe it is not lawful to poſſeſſe other liuinges, then ſuch as belong to the miniſterie, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I had no way to make vp the matter, or bring my purpoſe to paſſe, but onelye by hauing two or thrée benefices: and now you ſee the worlde what it is, howe that he that hath nothing ſhalbe nothing ſet by, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a good liuing and being able to beare ſome countenance, he may be a companion for a right good Gentleman: and I promiſe you, theſe were the cauſes that did moue me to take ſo many liuings, &amp; not for coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes ſake as you do imagine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Was it your chiefeſt regarde to haue greateſt reſpect vnto theſe vanities, I perceiue you are a right worldling, and by a wrong dore haue entred into the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, you ſay you did reſpect your calling, and that was how you were a gentleman: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut I perceiue you had forgotten another
<pb facs="tcp:176516:27"/>calling, which al miniſters ought to haue regarde vnto, and that is, that you are no longer called to be a gentleman, and to liue at eaſe: but if you will be the man that you ought to be, you muſt forſake your ſelfe and follow Chriſt, and as neer as you may imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate his ſteps, and then ſee what examples are laid before you, &amp; what a life you ought to liue. Chriſt him ſelfe, who although now heire of heauen &amp; earth, when the time was come, that he muſt be a miniſter of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, hee left heauen and the glory thereof, and tooke vpon him the ſhape of the ſeruant. <hi>Paul,</hi> which ſometimes was in authoritie beeing an enemie to the Goſpell, when it pleaſed God to make him a miniſter of the Goſpell, he was contented to forſake ſuche promotion, and<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 6.14.</note> reioice in nothing but in the croſſe of Chriſt. <hi>Mathewe</hi> ſitting<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 9.9.</note> at the receite of cuſtome, and in the middes of his worldlie affaires, when Chriſt ment to make him a Goſpeller, hee willingly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke all and followed him, <hi>Peter, Andrew, Iames,</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> which got their liuing by fiſhing and buſied about the ſame, ſome<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 4.18.</note> caſting their nets into the ſea, &amp; other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of their nets being broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which did re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quire
<pb facs="tcp:176516:27"/>ſome haſt, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt came by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; told the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he would make them fiſhers of men, they made no more adoe of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but left all and followed him, but you as thoughe you had a prerogatiue aboue Chriſt and his diſciples, thinke you may be a miniſter and a Gentleman too, that you may bee a Chriſtian and a worldling too, that you may ſerue God and the Diuel too, that you may liue at eaſe and yet beare the name of a painful labourer: but he that wil be a miniſter of the Goſpel, and a ſeruaunt to Chriſt, is taken on this condition, that if he wil looke to reign with him in his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, he muſt ſuffer for him a while in this world: and deny the vaine titles of a proud Prelate: and forſake the vanities of this vaine worlde: and to be be a<note n="*" place="margin">1. Tim. 4.12.</note> paterne to the godly, in word, in conuerſation, in charitie in faith, and in chaſtety, and to giue atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance vnto teaching, reading, doctrine and exhortation: this is the calling that you are called vnto, and as for the credit and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance that you ſeeke to haue in the world that you may be a companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch as are worldlinges, I will tell you (Maiſter par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) if you ſhape not to liue another kind of
<pb facs="tcp:176516:28"/>life, you wil one day be found a fit compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion for the diuell, you muſt beare with me though I bee ſomewhat plaine with you, and that which I tell you is nothing but trueth, and therefore I would wiſh you the ſooner to beleeue me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, I promiſe you, I will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue you for this matter, all the ſcripture you haue in your belly, will not make that ſinke into my head, that I being a miniſter ſhould forgoe the calling of a Gentleman, for if I had thought ſo much before I was miniſter, I wold neuer haue taken the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery vppon mee as long as I had liued: what is a miniſter now a dates without a liuing? and what is one benefice for a man to keepe houſe vpon? or how can he bid his friends welcome, &amp; giue them ſufficient en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment except he haue ſome other help aſ well? me thinks you being a gentleman, haue leaſt cauſe to complaine of any man, for I am ſure you &amp; your fellows fare neuer the worſe for vs of the miniſterie, eſpecially as many of vs as are vnmarried and haue no man to care for but our ſelues, we ſpare not to ſpend vpon good fellowes, and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman as you are, but you may come to
<pb facs="tcp:176516:28"/>our houſes at any time, when we are reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and be welcome. We keepe good hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes at Chriſtmas, we are merie &amp; haue our friendes about vs, and many a poore bodie at our gates doe fill their bellies with that which we leaue when our bellies are full.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>This is an Oration, that if it had bene made before the diuell, it woulde haue pleaſed him verye well: you are a man for his owne toothe, for I perceiue you are al for the bellie, and care neither for youre owne ſoule, nor the ſoules of ſuche as you ſhal anſwere for: but your greateſt deſire is to be in credite &amp; fauour with the worlde. I dare warrant you (M. Parſon) as long as you behaue you ſelfe in this order that you ſpeake of, you ſhal haue friendes y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowe in this world, and be alowde to haue recourſe to the diuel, which is the Prince of this worlde, &amp;<note n="*" place="margin">Ioſh. 2.13. Ephe. 6.21.</note> gouernour of ſuche as are worldlinges: but knowe this withal, that his kingdome doth laſt no longer then this worlde doth endure, and that wil haue an ende you knowe not how ſoone: &amp; although it be long before that time come: yet you ſhal beare no longer ſwaye in it then your owne life doth laſt, and that wil bee taken
<pb facs="tcp:176516:29"/>from you, it may be very ſhortly, and when your life is gone, your work will bee at an ende, and you ſhall haue your wages home with you, &amp; for the greedy deſire you haue had to fill your paunch, you ſhall haue fire &amp; br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mſton your belly full: &amp; for your<note n="*" place="margin">Eſay. 65.13. Luk. 8.24.</note> mirth &amp; merry paſtime, wherewith you thoughte your ſelfe neuer ſatiſfied, you ſhall haue more weeping and gnaſhing of teethe then you would deſire: and for the friendſhip you haue had in the worlde, you ſhall haue as much of the wrath of God as you are able to beare: and becauſe you haue ſerued your maſter the diuell diligently, you ſhal haue a loſſe in this, that ſhal laſt for euer. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (M. Parſon) if you like not of ſuch an alteration, I woulde wiſh you to lead a life of another faſhion, for ſuch ſweete meate will haue ſoure ſauce, and theſe plagues doth follow ſuch an vngodly life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Why, is there ſuch vngodlineſſe in vſing theſe thinges that I haue ſpoken of? or is it not commendable to keepe a good houſe, or to be merrie amongſt our friends.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>It is your duetie alwaies to bee a louer of<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Tim. 3.2.</note> hoſpitalitie: but in that you prefer one time before another, as your Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,
<pb facs="tcp:176516:29"/>which you ſpeake of, and ſuch like it may go amongſt the number of the reſt of your faultes, for the ſame fault did Sainte <hi>Paul</hi> finde amonſt the<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 4.10.</note> Galath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ans, and was in feare leaſt he had beſtowed his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour on them in vaine, becauſe they made a difference of da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, monethes, &amp; times, and where as you ſay, that the mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e which you leaue when your bellies are full, doth feede many poore at your gates: you may know that you thruſte them out of your gates, which ought to be gueſts at your tables.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>This is more then euer I hearde before, therefore I thinke it to be ſome new order of your owne making.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>If you thinke it ſtrange or a newe order, you may knowe that it was an order ſet down by our maſter Chriſte for a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand and fiue hundred yeres agone at the leaſt, that when wee made our feaſtes, wee ſhoulde<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 14.13.</note> call the poore, the maimed, the lame and the blinde: and not our friendes, our kinſmen, or rich neighbours, leaſt they recompence vs againe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I tell you plaine, this is a ſtrange order in deede in my iudgement, for I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe you, I neuer ſaw it on this faſhion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb facs="tcp:176516:30"/>neither doe I meane to beginne anye new orders, for I neuer made feaſt yet, nor neuer will againe, but I mind to haue my friends and kinſmen at it, that they maye do as much for mee another time, for if I had not vſed theſe meanes to get in credite amongſt my friends, and the gentlemen of our countrey, I had neuer had that whiche nowe I haue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Now it ddth plainly appear, what maſter you ſerue: for Chriſt diddeth you do one thing, and you ſhame not to ſay with open mouth, that you wil do clean contrary wherefore I may be a witnes, that you ſet more by the felowſhip of the world, then by the friendſhip of Chriſt: but I woulde wiſh you to take another order in your fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tings, and frame to liue another life, or elſe there is an order taken for you, that you ſhal bee accurſed, and al that you haue.<note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 28.16.</note> Curſſed ſhal you be in the Citie, and curſed in the field, curſed ſhall bee your baſket and your ſtore, curſed ſhall bee the increaſe of your kine, and the flockes of your ſheepe, curſed ſhal you bee when you goe out, and curſed when you come home, &amp; al that you take in hand ſhalbe accurſed, if you ſerue not God.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:30"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Alaſſe what wil you haue me to do? you know I am no preacher, and therefore cannot giue them ſpirituall foode, it is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that I ſhould feede them one waie or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, for you haue tolde me that a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard muſt feede his flocke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Alas, what meant you to take that worke in hand, which you cannot tel howe to labour in? whie haue you taken vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you the office of a preacher, and yet ſay you can not preach? whie haue you this long borne the name of a ſhepheard, and know nor yet how to feede your ſheepe, whie haue you entred as a workman into the Lordes har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, and doe beſtowe al your time in lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and idlenes, whie are you let to keepe the wolfe from the ſheepe, and are a dumb dogge that cannot barke, howe hath the diuel bewitched you, and ſet you a feeding onlie of their bodies, while he in the mean time goeth aboute, readie to deuoure bothe bodies and ſoules: leaue of leaue of for ſhame (maſter Parſon) and bee no longer deceiued &amp; led away with the ſubtil ſlights of Satan: for let him tel you what hee wil, and ſo blinde your eies that you can not ſee your ſinne, yet although you haue atteined
<pb facs="tcp:176516:31"/>to great liuings, and are not without three benefices: becauſe you are no preacher of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel of Chriſt, you ought not to keep one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Then I would I were a preacher, for then I thinke you coulde be contented y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I ſhould haue liuing inought.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>In deede as it is good reaſon that he that will not<note n="*" place="margin">2 Theſs. 3.10</note> labour ſhould not eate, ſo is it as good reaſon that they that<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.14. Luk. 10.7.</note> preache the Goſpell, and ſuch<note n="*" place="margin">1. Tim. 5.18.</note> as labour faithfully ſhould be well rewarded.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Then I ſee well, if I could preach, you could be contented that I ſhould keepe my three benefices.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>No (maſter parſon) I ſaid not ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>No? did you not ſay that hee that did labour faithfully ſhoulde haue enough?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, but I did not ſay that he ſhould haue too much.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Why, do you think three benefices to much for a good preacher?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, I thinke three benefices to be two to manie for him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> can preach beſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What doe you thinke ſo? then I would there were a preacher here that hath three or foure benefices, that he might aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere for himſelfe: but for want of ſuche a
<pb facs="tcp:176516:31"/>one, I doubt not, but mee ſelfe am able e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to defende ſo good a cauſe: for if it were not lawful for him that can preach to haue two benefices, it muſt needes be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull for me to haue three which am no preacher.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>In deede you ſay true, therefore I pray you (maſter parſon) let me heere what you can ſay, &amp; what ſkil you haue to make darkneſſe lighte, and light darkneſſe, euill good, and good euill, the hauing of two or three benefices for one man to bee lawfull, which in the ſight of God is moſte abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>You haue tolde mee that there is nothing required of a Paſtor, but to preach the word, and féed his flocke, and this may one man do, in three or foure benefices very well: for you knowe by the lawes of the realme, that if euery pariſly haue a ſermon once in a quarter of a yeere, it is ſufficient.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What (maſter parſon) you ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the lawes of the reaime, for I knowe there is no law to the contrary, but that the miniſter maye preach euery Sabboth day: by the lawe of God hee oughte not to<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 20.28. 2. Tim. 4.2.</note> neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect any time, that hee may beſtowe in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing
<pb facs="tcp:176516:32"/>and feeding of his flocke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>But doe you not thinke, that this may be ſufficiently done, in preaching once in a quarter of a yeare?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>If the Diuell woulde appoint two too meete the Shepheard there cuerie quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſo trie who might haue the victory, and neuer came amongſt the ſheepe, but at ſuch time as the ſhepherd is ther, it were y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: but becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuel, as a Wolfe doth alwaies and at all times, ſeeks the deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſhéep, therfore the miniſter as a good Shepheard, ought continually to bee watching, and ready to withſtand him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>In deede I muſte needes confeſe, that it were beſt if it might be ſo, but ſéeing the caſe ſtandeth as it doth, that there are not Preachers ynough to place in euerye pariſh one, is it not better thinke you, that one Preacher haue three or foure benefices that can teach the flocke ſometimes? then to haue a doult that can ſaye nothing at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Here (M. Parſon) you haue giuen your ſelfe a ſore blowe, which are amongſt the number of the dolts, whom you ſpeacke off.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:32"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>But you muſt imagine, that what I ſay now for others, is but for talkes ſake and not condemne my ſelfe, neither do I thinke the worſe of my ſelfe, what euer I ſay: for I knowe if you had had this talke with a Preacher, he woulde haue ſaide as much for me, but this doth not anſwere the queſtion, do you not think it better to haue the flocke fed at ſometimes, then not at all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Truely I am of this minde, that it were as good neuer a whit, as neuer the better.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>In deede that is true, but you muſt not thinke but that it wil be ſomewhat the better, for although at I muſt needes faye that the continuall preſence of the Paſtors be moſte proſitable, yet I thinke not the contrary, but that if it be ſo that hee maye come amongeſt his flocke but ſeldeine, yet that wil doe them much good: for I praie you, let me aſke you this queſtion: if one of them hauing <hi>2.</hi> benefices, in both which hee cannot at one time be reſident, if hee ſpend halfe in another, is it not almoſte as good as if hee. were alwayes at one of
<pb facs="tcp:176516:33"/>them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>This difference there is, that where as the careful miniſter being alwaies reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to defend his ſheepe from their enemie the diuell (which doth continually watche for ſpoil, being ready to deuour them) maye ſtande them in as good ſteede as a ſtrong defence, againſt al the aſſaultes of Satan: ſo ſuch a one as you ſpeake of, that is a long time from them, may haue (in his abſence) his flocke ſcattered, and ſo hee himſelfe bee found a negligent ſhepheard.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>But he may ſo applie them at his being amongſt them, that they ſhal be able to ſpare him a while without any danger.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Truely (M. Parſon) I can tel you, the diuel is a ſubtil byrd, and the ſhepheard ſhall no ſooner bee from his flocke, but hee wil be amongſt them, and if the miniſter haue two benefices, when hee is at one, the diuell will be at another, ſo that you maye now ſee howe needefull it is for the Paſtor to be alwaies amongſt his flocke, ſince Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan is ſo greedie to worke them their vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deſtruction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>But if all this that I haue tolde you will not ſuffice, yet if the worſt fal out,
<pb facs="tcp:176516:33"/>they that haue ſo many liuinges that they cannot be at them al at one time, maye in their abſence, place honeſt miniſters that may ſupplie their rooure, almoſt as well as themſelues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What doe you meane? that others ſhal feede, an they will ſheere, that they ſhal haue the hier, and others do the work? that they ſhall but beare the name of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, and liue by the ſweate of other mens browes? is this that you meane by others ſupplying of the roome?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Truely my meaning is, that in the abſence of the paſtors, he ſhoulde place one amongſt his flocke, that may keepe them in order?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What woulde you that he ſhoulde onely receiue the fruites for him? and take vp his tithes, an ſhere his ſheepe in due time, and by that meanes keep them in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I meane that there ſhoulde bee an honeſt man ſet ouer them, that may ſeede as well as ſhere.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>And who ſhall haue the fleeſe mean you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>It is reaſon that the Parſon of the
<pb facs="tcp:176516:34"/>pariſhe haue the fruites of his benefice, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he be not alwaies reſident, and the miniſter that doth ſupplie his roome, maie haue ſome reaſonable matter, according as he doth deſerue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Then he muſt haue all, for I haue ſhewed you out of the Scripture, that the<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 10.7.</note> laborer is worthie of his hire, but he that wil not labor<note n="*" place="margin">1. Tim. 5.18. 2. The. 3.10.</note> ſhould not eate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Although you haue ſcripture, that doth make for your purpoſe, yet there are verie good reaſons for the which a miniſter may verie well, and for good conſideration be abſent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Haue you ſo good reaſon for it (M. Parſon) I knowe there is no reaſon that is contrary to the ſcripture, for althoughe you dreame of reaſon, and thinke to prefer your owne deuiſes before the word of God yet what euer you ſaie touching theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, although it ſéeme neuer ſo reaſonable if it agree not with the worde of God, it is altogether without reaſon: but I prate you what are your reaſons that you thinke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>For this cauſe I thinke a miniſter maie verie well be abſent from his flocke
<pb facs="tcp:176516:34"/>as if he bee but a young ſcholler, and is like to profit by being in the vniuerſitie a while, whereby he maie be able (for euer after) the better to diſcharge his duetie: maie hee not for ſo good a conſideration (for a while) bee a non reſident.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Did you neuer heare this prooued (maſter Parſon) that (many times) whiles the graſſe groweth, the horſe ſtarueth? ſo no doubt of it, is it with ſuch a miniſter that is yet to learne, and hath taken vpon him the office of a teacher: while hee is in the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerſitie fraighting of himſelf with learning to bring home to his flocke, manie a ſillie ſheepe doth in the meane time periſhe for lacke of knowledge, &amp; this did ſaint Paule verie well know, and therefore hee woulde haue a miniſter not to be<note n="*" place="margin">1. Time. 3.6.</note> a young ſcholler: but ſuch a one as is<note n="*" place="margin">ver. 10.</note> alreadie able to take care of his charge, and<note n="*" place="margin">2. Time. 2.24.</note> apt to teach, before he take ſo waightie a matter in hand.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Then if it be ſo that hee muſt firſt be a good ſcholler, and able to teache before he take on him the miniſterie, there is good reaſon that hee ſhoulde vſe the meanes that he may continue his knowledge, and therfore hee maie lawfullie be alowed, two
<pb facs="tcp:176516:35"/>or three benefices, that he may furniſh him ſelfe like a ſcholler, and prouide him books, without the which he cannot ſtudie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Why are they nowe ſo deare that they muſt ſell ſoules, to buy bookes? you doe not ſee howe you ouerſhoote your ſelfe in your talke (maſter Parſon) for you thinke it no matter, though many ſoules goe to the diuell ſo that one mans ſtudy may be well furniſhed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I know there be ſome that coulde anſwere you for theſe matters if they were here, and prooue that they maye lawfully haue more benefices then you are willing that they ſhould, for ther are ſome that are very good ſchollers, and knowe what they doe, and yet they are not amongſt their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners ſkarſe once in halfe a yere: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am fully perſiwaded that euen the very name of a preacher, if it bee nothing els, although be neuer (almoſt) come amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt his flocke, will doe ſome good, doe you not thinke ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke the name of a Preacher onely, will doe the people ſo much good, as the ſmell of a meſſe of pottage to a hungrie bodye, or an empty potte to a thirſtie ſoule:
<pb facs="tcp:176516:35"/>which is no good at all, but doth cauſe him to languiſh in vaine, with an earneſt deſire to haue that which hee can not obteine: If this be al that you can ſay, maſter Parſon, I perceiue you want ſkill to defende ſo bad a cauſe, yea and ſo doe they that thinke them ſelues beſte able to ſay moſte in the matter: and vnder that pretence of a loue to the people (for lucres ſake) they ſeeke the deſtruction of them ſelues, and ſuche as are their charge: they feed onely themſelues and are ſuch as the prophet Ezechiel cryed woe vnto,<note n="*" place="margin">Ezech. 34.3.</note> they eate vp the fat (ſayth hee) and cloth them with the wooll, the beſt fed do they ſlay, but the ſheep they do not feed, the weake they haue not ſtrengthened, the ſicke they haue not healed, the broken they haue not bound togeather, the driuen away they haue not brought againe, the loſt they haue not ſought, but with force and cruelty they rule them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Me thinkes there ſhoulde not be all theſe faultes in them that you ſpeake of, for there are ſome of them that are very, good fellowes, and keep good houſes, which doth deſerue great commendations.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>In deede there are ſome of them
<pb facs="tcp:176516:36"/>that loue to fare well, and can make their gueſts good cheere, but this is not it, (M. Parſon) that they ought onelie to bee care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for, nor it is not ſuch ſacrifice that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God: for do you thinke that the Lorde will be bolde with your owne inuentions, which the vanitie of your own brains hath brought forth: with the keeping of a great houſe for great men, and feeding onlie the bodies of the people, when as the Lorde doth chieflie require that the ſoule, (which is the principalleſt part) ſhould be beſt fed? or will you giue the fruites of your benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for the ſinne of your ſoule? or doe you thinke that the Lorde hath as greate plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in burnt offernings, as when his voiyce is obeyed? No (M. Parſon) know it, and knowe it ſo well that you neuer forget it, that to<note n="*" place="margin">1. Sam. 15.22.</note> obey is better then ſacrifice, and to harken is better then the fat of Rams: for rebellion is as the ſinne of witchcraft, and ſtubberneſſe is as the wickedneſſe of idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, whoſe rewarde is an euerlaſting life full of continuall miſerie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I marnaile that other men as wiſe as you, can not ſee theſe faultes as well as you, (if theſe bee faultes) I woulde
<pb facs="tcp:176516:36"/>faine know the cauſe thereof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Truely I can ſhewe yon no other cauſe, nor knowe not to what and they giue themſelues to the loue of ſo manie liuings, but only for the deſire of filthie lucre, which doth ſpring of a conetous minde, which is the roote of all euill: and now may we take vp againe the complaint of the Prophet, <note n="*" place="margin">Iere, 24.2.</note> like prieſt, like people, that<note n="*" place="margin">Iere. 6.13.</note> from the leſt vnto the moſt, they hang all vpon couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and from the Prophet vnto the prieſt they go about falſhood and lyes, the prieſtes<note n="*" place="margin">Miche. 3.11.</note> preache for lucre, and the Prophetes propheſie for gaine, but<note n="*" place="margin">Iud. 11.</note> woe be vnto them for they haue gone the way of Caine, and are vtterly giuen ouer to the erroure of <hi>Balaam</hi> for Iucres ſake: and without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment ſhall periſhe in the gaineſaying of <hi>Cora,</hi> they are ſuch as <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh of, that can<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 2.22.</note> teach others and not them ſelues, they preach that a man ſhoulde not ſteale, yet they ſteale: they abhorre Idols, and yet commit ſacriledge: they make their boaſt of the lawe, and yet through breaking of the law they diſhonour God, and cauſe his name to be euill ſpoken of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What thinke you of theſe doctors
<pb facs="tcp:176516:37"/>which are men of great learning, and of the number of thoſe whome we ſpeake of, howe is it poſſible they ſhould ſo be deceiued:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you (M. Parſon) can you tell mee what was the cauſe that all the words which Pharaoh heard from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, and all the myracles that were wroughte before him, coulde not make him to obeye God, but ſtill to conſtinue in his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe before hee was ouergotten in his ſinne?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I haue hearde that it was becauſe his heart was hardened.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay very true, for that<note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 14.17.</note> was the onely cauſe therof, and the ſame diſeaſe of hardneſſe of heart hath taken ſuch holde in the ſtomackes of theſe whom we ſpeake of, that it hath made them ſo ſicke, that (I feare me) it hath brought many of them to their graues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>If it be true that they are deceined, I maruel why they ſeek to bear the names of doctors, and to couet ſuch promotion as many of them are in.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>I know not (for my part) what to thinke them, nor what they meane by theſe glorious titles and great liuings, but
<pb facs="tcp:176516:37"/>that they are ſuch as Chriſte ſpake of, that<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 23.6.</note> loue the vppermoſt ſeats at feaſts, and to ſit in the cheefe places of the Sinagogues, and loue greetings in the Market places, and to be called of men Rabbi, Rabbi</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What, can you ſee nothing elſe in them but that? then I perceiue I can ſee more then you, for ſuche as they are, that heare the names of doctors, &amp; are in ſome credite and eſtimation amongſt the people, ſhal the ſooner be beléeued in that they ſay, and the worde that they preach will be the better imbraced.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Oh (M. Parſon) you are deceiued in your ſight, I thinke you lack your ſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacles that you can ſee no better: if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God ſhould work more in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, being deliuered of great men, and ſuch as are in authoritie, I maruel that Chriſte had not foreſeene it, which was equall with his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in glorie, and yet made himſelfe of no reputation during the time of his being v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the earth, when he had alwaies a care to goe about his fathers buſineſſe, whiche was to preach the goſpell, that as many as were ordeined vnto eternallife, might haue redemption through him in his hloude, and
<pb facs="tcp:176516:38"/>why had he not choſen the great and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie men of the world, and made them his Diſciples? but choſe rather poore Fiſhers &amp; men of no eſtimation in the worlde, to be miniſters of his word, &amp; diſtributers of his miſteries: but you are deceiued (M. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) and that is true which Sainte Paule ſaithe, that<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 1.27.</note> God hath choſen the fooliſh things of this world, to conſound the wiſe, and the weake things of the worlde to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the mightie, and things of no repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation &amp; deſpiſed, to bring to naught thoſe thinges that are highly eſſteemed, that no fleſh ſhould reioice in his ſight.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>For all this, I cannot yet be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, but that it is lawful for a preacher to haue as manie benefices as he can get: &amp; he that cannot preache, maie haue three or four, and be verie wel diſpenſed withal: for you ſee that it is ſo, and if it ought not to be ſo, men are worſe then madde to doe that which is not lawfull.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>In deede it is too true, that it is ſo with the moſt parte (although not with all) and therein they ſhewe their madneſſe, for amongſt a great many of them, onelye a fewe ercepted, which the Lorde dothe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue to himſelfe, and hath giuen better
<pb facs="tcp:176516:38"/>heartes vnto, if hee be once a miniſter, hee thinkes by and by that hee is made onelye to get him manie liuinges: and if hee bee a Preacher and haue a wife and children, he hath a conſcience large ynough, to wiſh for as many benefices as he can get: but if his greedie deſire can not ſo be ſatiſfied: yet if it bee poſſible, he will haue three at the leaſt, one for himſelfe, another for his wife, and a thirde for his children, and that they maye haue theſe liuinges to maintaine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſo, that they may goe amongſt the Gallants of the worlde, that their diet may be of the beſt, their tables traught with all kinde of dainties, and that they may not be behind hand, but in their apparel as braue as the proudeſt, themſelues in their ſilkes, their wiues in their trench hoodes, and their children parinted like puppets, &amp; that they may a while enioy this geare, and liue at eaſe in this worlde, they care neither what ſhal become of themſelues, their wiues and their children in the world to come: but are contented flock and al ſhal go to the Diuel, for any farther care they take for them. Is this to<note n="*" place="margin">Iohn. 21.15.</note> feede, feede, feede, as Chriſte ſaid vnto Peter: Nay this is rater to kill,
<pb facs="tcp:176516:39"/>kil, kil, as the Sheepe that are led to the ſlaughter, I thinke if the Prophet Ieremy were now liuing, and did ſee the lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble eſtate of our time, be woulde ſay for vs, as he did for the people in his time, that he could finde in his heart to<note n="*" place="margin">Iere. 9.1.</note> weepe daie and night, for the ſlaughter of the people. Oh that their hearts were circumciſed, and the vilens of their eies taken from them, that they might once ſee &amp; vnderſtand, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> to haue ſo great a charge, that ſome muſt needes periſhe for wante of looking vnto, and to ſhere the ſheepe, and not to feede the flocke, is to<note n="*" place="margin">Iohn. 10.10.</note> ſpoile, murther, and deſtroye: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what euer he bee, or by what title ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he be called, whether he be a doctour by name, a Parſon of manie benefices, or Sir <hi>Iohn Lacklatin,</hi> that can ſaie nothing: if hee haue no more regarde, but to ſatiſfie his owne greedie deſire, and is careleſſe for the ſafetie of ſuch as doe paie him for a better worke, let him think of himſelfe as wel as he liſt, yet theſe are the titiles that hee doth beſt deſerue, doctor <hi>Spoiles,</hi> Parſon <hi>Theefe</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn Murtherer,</hi> for in taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie of the goodes from their Pariſhioners (without doing of their dutie) is before the
<pb facs="tcp:176516:39"/>maieſtie of God no better then theft: and to let their ſoules periſh for want of foode, is to be a murtherer and ſpoiler of the ſoules of them which Chriſte did ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d his bloude for.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>But mee thinkes you mighte vſe milder ſpeeches, for ther are manie of theſe I tel you, that are of good wiſedome, and beare ſome countenance, and therefore wil take it, as an offence, to haue theſe names at your hands.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Are they aſhamed to bear y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> names, and doe they take no ſhame to deſerue the names? doe they ſet more by the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the worlde, then by the fauoure of God? haue they a more deſire to pleaſe men then they haue to ſerue Chriſte? can they w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> braſen brows, commit ſuch faultes in open places, &amp; are they not aſhamed ſo to offend before the Lorde and his Angels? doe they rather chuſe to liue at eaſe a while in this tranſitorie worlde, then to line for euer in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world that neuer ſhould haue end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or wil they perſecute Chriſt in his members, and yet ſaie ſtil, they are good Chriſtians. If it be true, they ſhew their vnſdome that it is nothing but follie, and if they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to bee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended
<pb facs="tcp:176516:40"/>with him that giueth them theſe names, let them looke in the tenth of Ihon and there they ſhal find, that he that regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not his flocke, is<note n="*" place="margin">Iohn. 10.</note> a theefe, &amp; commeth for nothing but to ſpoile, kil, and deſtroie: &amp; he that ſpake the words, is Chriſt himſelfe, and if becauſe they cannot touch him, they wilbe offended with mee, that haue ſaide it after him, they ſhalbe ſure to make a wrong matche: for in ſo good cauſe I knowe Chriſt wil take my parte, and hauing him on my ſide. I care not though al the worlde were ſet againſt me: for if the Lord himſlef take the matter in hand, mark howe his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimies are like to ſpeed, he can fight with them, form heauen<note n="*" place="margin">Ioſua. 10.11.</note> with hailſtones, as hee did for his ſeruant Ioſua. He can ſend them as much<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 19.24.</note> fire and Brimſton, that ſhal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume them al, as he did the Sodomites. He can cauſe the earth to open and<note n="*" place="margin">Num. 16.32.</note> ſwallowe them vp quicke, as hee did <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> with theire wicked compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, if they thinke themſelues ſo ſtrong &amp; ſo manie in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nmber, that their aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are not able to withſtand them: God is able in ſteede of other help, to cauſe one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to kil<note n="*" place="margin">Iud. 7.22.</note> another, as it fel out amongſt the
<pb facs="tcp:176516:40"/>Madianites, and if there be any that doe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape the ſword, and flie vnto houſes for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>coure: God is able to throwe downe the<note n="*" place="margin">3. Kin. 20.30</note> walles vpon them, as he did vpon the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, which at one time ſlewe ſeuen and twentie thouſand, if ſuch as are left wil con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinue ſtil deriding the ſeruaunts of God, he is able to ſend as maine ſhee<note n="*" place="margin">4. Kin. 2.24.</note> Beares oute of the woodes as ſhal deuour them al, as he did for ſuch as mocked his ſeruant <hi>Eliſeus,</hi> and if this bee not ynough, there is no miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheefe that they would wiſh to fal vpon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but God is able to make it fal on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, this can the Lorde doe, and greater thinges then theſe, for what is it? but that is poſſible with him: but although he doeth with patience endure the wickedneſſe of his enemies for a while, yet he can and wil at length, plague them through lie, to their vtter deſtruction: and for his owne ſeruants althoughe theire enemies rage, as doe the waues of the ſea: yet ſhal they not goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde the boundes, that the Lorde hath ſet them, if they would caſt them into priſous, thinking by that means to vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at their pleaſure, God is able to ſend his<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 5.16.</note> Angel to open the doores vnto them, as he did for his
<pb facs="tcp:176516:41"/>Apoſtles, &amp; by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meanes ſet them at liberty If they wold thruſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into the fierie ouen, thinking that waie to conſume them, God is able ynough to keepe them from<note n="*" place="margin">Dan. 3.25.</note> bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as he did <hi>Sidrach, Miſach,</hi> and <hi>Abed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nega,</hi> If they woulde caſt them amongſt the Lions, thinking that way to deſtroy them: God is able to ſtop<note n="*" place="margin">Dan. 6.22.</note> their mouthes: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they ſhall not hurt them, as he did for <hi>Daniel,</hi> If they woulde keepo them from meate, that they might kil them with hunger, God is able to cauſe the<note n="*" place="margin">3. Kin. 17.9.</note> Kauens to feede them, as he did for <hi>Elias,</hi> If they woulde make a Gallowes to diſpatche others, God can cauſe them to bee hanged thereon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: as it fel oute betweene wicked<note n="*" place="margin">Eſter. 7.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Haman,</hi> and good <hi>Mardocheus,</hi> all this can the Lorde doe for ſuche as ſerue him faithfully: but although he ſuffer them to be perſecuted for a while, yet he can and wil at length, deliuer them oute of their enemies hands: though they were as many in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as al the people in the worlde, and as terrible to looke on as al the Diuelles in Hell, yet ſhal they once haue the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory: and al their foes ſhal bee made their footeſtoole, and ſhal bee faine to confeſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:176516:41"/>though ſore againſt their willes, that ſuche honour ſhall all the Saints of God be ſure to haue, therefore (M. Parſon) if theſe men whome you ſpeake of, be ſo whſe as you make them, they wil beware how they plai the fooles, and take heede that they hurt not Chriſtes annointed, and doe his Prophetes no harme.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>They ſhall anſwere for themſelues for me, you are ſo full of the ſcripture, that I know not what to make of you: I maruel y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> your father had not made you a miniſter, ſince you are giuen to bee ſo holy, When I was made miniſter, I had no ſcripture at all, and yet my father did perſwade mee that I was fit inough for that function.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What did hee ſo? the more foole your father, and the greater was his ſinne: did he meane to make you a teacher before you were a good ſcholler? or had he ſo little regarde of his childe, that he coulde finde in his hart to ſet you in ſuch a place, that you muſt needes runne to the Diuell headlong: a great token of an vnnatural Father. But althoughe your Father were careleſſe in theſe matters, and had no regarde to that which was chiefeſt to bee ſought for: yet I
<pb facs="tcp:176516:42"/>maruell, how the viſhop did let you eſcape, finding you ſo vnmeete for that office, for it is his duetie to examine you, and (as Saint Paule ſaith)<note n="*" place="margin">1. Tim. 3.10.</note> a miniſter muſt firſt be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued before he bee alowed to miniſter: and were not you ſo examined and prooued (M. Parſon?)</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Yes that I was, and that through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What were you ſo? I praie you (if you remember them) what were the queſtions that the biſhop did propoſe you? and after what maner did hee examine you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I will tell you what they were, for I do verie well remember them, and ſhall neuer forget them, as long as I liue, this was the manner of mine examination: when I came to the Biſhop, and be vnder, ſtoode that my comming was to bee made miniſter, he would not admit me, nor grant me my letters of orders, before he had exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined me whether I were able to paie for them or no, and when I had anſwered him yea, yet he would not ſo be ſatiſfied, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I was a yong man, and not worthie to be beleeued at the firſt, he would needes
<pb facs="tcp:176516:42"/>examine me farther, where I had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mony a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bout me or no, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I had told him yea, yet he would not ſo be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented, but he muſt haue it out of hand, that he might examine my mony, whether it were as much as hee would haue or no: and my Lorde finding it to his minde, and that I had anſwered him verie Clarklike to euerie queſtion, he was verie well ſatiſfied, and to be made miniſter I was graunted: and then to his officer for my letters of orders I muſt goe, and there I muſt be prooued, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I came to him, he ſeing that I was a yong man, and but a reaſonable Clarke, &amp; did conſider with him ſelfe that I mighte commit manie faults before I came to olde age, he woulde needes prooue me whether I would beſtow a bribe on him or no, to ſpeake a good worde for me vnto my Lorde if need did ſo require, and I hauing granted him is requeſt: ſuch of the biſhops men, as did know what I was and vnderſtood of my liberallitie, they wold needes prooue alſo, whether I woulde do as much for them, &amp; they would dor any thing they could for me: &amp; thus I was prooued of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt part of my Lordes men, and they had prooued mée ſo long, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> at laſt I was able to
<pb facs="tcp:176516:43"/>prooue that they had not left me a penie in my purſe, now iudge you whether I were examined and prooued or no?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, I muſt needes ſaie that you were both examined &amp; prooued, for they had prooued you ſo long til they had prooued you a verie foole, in beſtowing your mony vpon ſuch lewde fellowes as did loue to liue by bribes: belike my lord (their maſter) neuer taught his ſeruants the ſtory of <hi>Gehezi</hi> (the ſeruant of <hi>Elizeus</hi>) and how he ſped for his labor, which for his bribing became<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Kin. 5.27.</note> a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per as white as ſnowe: is this the proofe that they vſe to make of miniſters?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What it is now I know not, for this that I tell you of was done for long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe: but I thinke it be otherwiſe now.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>So it had neede, or elſe it is ſtarke naught: for they ought to haue prooued and examined, whether that had beene in you which is required of a miniſter, as to bee<note n="*" place="margin">1. Tim. 3.2.</note> blameleſſe, ſober, waiting, apt to teache, not gréedie of filthie lucre, and ſuch like: but by your owne ſaying there was not a word of that matter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Truelie no otherwiſe then I tolde you.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:43"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>I praie you what good counſel did your father giue you, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he (ment to make you a miniſter) ſeeing you were ſo vnable to do anie thing of your ſelfe, did he promiſe that if you did not diſcharge your duetie, he would go to the diuel for you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>No, he ment nothing leſſe: but this counſell he gaue me, that I ſhoulde ſeeke to pleaſe all men as neere as I might, &amp; that I ſhould take heede of my ſelfe: for beeing once a miniſter, euery man would be on my iack, and it would be, who that might haue a fling at me, and theſe words haue I found true, &amp; my fathers counſel haue I alwaies folowed, and I doe what I maie to get the good will of all men, I am free harted, and ſpare not to ſpend euen all that I haue, for of three hundred markes, which I receiue by the yere: I can not fetch three hundreth pence at the yeares ende: I am a good fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and as I receiue it of my pariſhioners ſo I ſpend it amongſt them againe, neither am I high minded, as manie of you gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen are, whom a man maie not ſpeake withall vnder a couple of Capons: I can drinke a Pot of Ale with a good fellowe at anie time, and can ſit at Cardes or Tables
<pb facs="tcp:176516:44"/>a whole day together, and am contented to be a companion (in theſe matters) for the meaneſt in my pariſhe: and thus doe I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow my time, and ſpende my money in goodfellowſhip, for I haue no man to care for but my ſelfe, and therefore I knowe not for whom I ſhould keepe it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Are you ſo good a fellow (Maſter Parſon) as you ſpeake of? Beware that it be not ſuch fellowſhip as the Apoſtle ſpake of, when he ſaid that the<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am. 4.4.</note> fellowſhip of this world is enemitie with God: &amp; in that you ſaie you haue no man to care for, appeareth the little care you haue of thoſe for wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you ſhall anſwere for: haue you taken vpon you to be a Sheepheard, and can you be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be fed of your ſheepe? will you there their f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſes and ſell their ſkins? will you for this promiſe to bring them to good paſure that they maie be fed vnto eternal life, &amp; yet ſaie ſtil you haue no man to care for? Well, wel (M. Parſon) this geare muſt bee loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vnto in time, or els for your careleſneſſe you ſhall be ſure to anſwere.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>You miſtake me Syr, I meane not my Pariſhioners, which I knowe are my tharge, but my meaning is, I haue no wife
<pb facs="tcp:176516:44"/>nor any childe for whome I neede to care for.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Then I perceiue you are not mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>No in deed I am not, neither doe I meane to marrie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Why? doe you not thinke it lawfull for one of your calling to marrie, or haue you that gift of chaſtitie, that you neede no ſuch helpe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>As touching chaſtitie, I am a man as another man is, but how lawfull it is for a prieſt to marrie, I coulde neuer as yet at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the knowledge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What are you a teacher, and haue not yet learned ſo muche? truely by mine aduiſe, before you had been allowed a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, you ſhould firſt haue prooued your ſelfe a better ſcholler. What can you ſaie for the defence of ſo wicked an opinion, is not the word of God a Lantern to your ſteps, and a guid vnto your pathes? If not, no maruell though you be out of the waie: doth not S. Paul ſaie? that to<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 7.2.</note> auoide fornicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man haue his wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e? how dare you then ſaie that Miniſters may not marrie? If you can prooue them to be no men, I will agree
<pb facs="tcp:176516:45"/>with you, if not, I praie you anſwere me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What Saint Paule ſaith, I can not tell, but I can ſhewe you good reaſon whie a miniſter ſhould not marrie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Haue you ſo good reaſons for it (M. Parſon) I praie you let me heare ſome of them, that I maie bee acquainted with them, and I will promiſe you, if you can ſhew me better reaſons, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſters ought not to marrie, then I can ſhewe you to the contrarie, I will binde my ſelfe to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable vnto you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>You know that miniſters can not aſſure their wife nor children of any liuing: and is it not better (thinke you) that they remaine vnmarried, then to fill the world ful of beggers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>But you knowe that all haue not the gift of chaſtitie, and is it not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etter (thinke you) that they marrie, then to fill the world full of baſtards?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>As for that matter, there are many ſhiftes, ſo that although a miniſter be not married, he neede not to bee troubled with manie baſtards.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What your ſhifts are (M. Parſon) that you vſe I know not, but this I am ſure of, that if you haue not the gifte of chaſtitie,
<pb facs="tcp:176516:45"/>you were better<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 7.9.</note> to marrie then to burne: therefore, M. Parſon, if you finde not that gift in you, I wold wiſh you to take a wife of your owne in the feare of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What, would you haue me to haue a wife of mine owne? fye vpon her, naie, yet I had rather to take a ſnatch ſometimes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt my neighbours, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue a wife of mine owne, what if there ſhould come an alteration, and the lawes ſhoulde change, I pray you in what caſe ſhoulde married miniſters be then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>But what if you ſhould finde an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration before that time, and from a proud prelate become a firebrand in hell, in what caſe I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay you ſhould you be in then? for I can tell you, that<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 13.4.</note> whoremongers, and and adulterers, God wil iudge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>As for that take you no care, for you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be no iudge of the matter, neither for al your thretninges can I be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that it is lawful for miniſters to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, but if they would needes marrie, they muſt be married to their bookes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What would you haue a man mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to a booke? I perceiue you knowe not wherefore matrimonie was ordeined.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:46"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, ſo ſimple a ſcholler as you make me, I know ſo much.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Then I truſt you remember, that God ſaide vnto man and woman<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 1.20.</note> increaſe and multiply, and if you wil haue a popiſh prieſt married to a Maſſe booke, the Diuel may bee a goſſip to the childe that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, and Sainte Paule ſaith that it is the<note n="*" place="margin">Tim. 4.1.</note> doctrine of diuels to forbid marriage, and that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> latter daies there ſhould be ſome of that wicked opinion, of the which num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber (I feare me) you are one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>You are al in S. Paul, and nothing but ſcripture, I would fain haue you ſhewe me ſome doctor that mighte make for your warrant, amongeſt al our talke you haue not recited one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>No: I maruell that you are ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getful, haue I not laide before you many doctors?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>None, to my remembrance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>No, did I not recite you, Doctor Eſay, Doctor Ieremy, Doctor Peter, and Doctor Paule?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What, doe you account them doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors? they be but Prophets and Apoſtles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What (M. Parſon) doe you make
<pb facs="tcp:176516:46"/>a but of them? I praye you who are they that you account doctors?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I meane Auguſtine, Cyprian, Ierome, and their fellowes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Are there none Doctors but theſe thinke you? I pray you how wil you know a Doctor?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I wil knowe a Doctor by his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>That is very well ſaid, and doe you thinke theſe men whom you ſpeake of, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter learned, then Prophetes and Apoſtles, which were taught of God himſelfe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>No, I doe not thinke ſo: but yet theſe are they that our frefathers haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken holde on, to defend their opinions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What our fathers haue done, to vs it ſhall not ſkil, or what opinions they held we neede not care for, but if your doctours agree with our Doctours, wee agree with them, if not, wee wil leaue Auguſtine, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome, and their fellowes, and learne of the Prophetes and Apoſtles, which are their maſters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I perceiue (Gentleman) it is a great matter whereof you can ſay nothing, and for your kowledge I muſt néeds com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende
<pb facs="tcp:176516:47"/>you, but becauſe youre eie ſighte is good, that you can finde ſo manye faultes in other men, me thinkes your own life ſhould be ſuch as dothe aunſwere your profeſſion, therefore if I might bee ſo bold to intreate you, I would craue to know what hath bin your bringing vp, and how in theſe dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous daies you ſhape to liue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Your commendations doth farre exceede my deſert, but to fulfill your deſire to know mine eſtate, I wil be as readie to ſhew you, as you are to heare it, but ſorie I am to leaue you no better perſwaded, then yet I finde you: but in hope that the Lorde wil worke more in you, after you haue pauſed a while, I wil keepe promiſe with you touching my ſelfe, and talke more of your owne eſtate anon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>But before you goe anie further (Gentleman) I ſhal firſt deſire you that I maie be ſo bolde to know your name.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What, would you ſo faine know my name (M. Parſon) I wil not ſticke with you in ſo ſmal a matter, neither is my name ſuche that I ſhoulde refuſe to ſhewe it you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Then (I praie you ſir) what is it?</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:47"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>My name is <hi>Chistopher Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What are you a Gentleman, and are you called <hi>Conſcience?</hi> mee thinkes it is an vnfit name for you, as might be deuiſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Whie ſhould you think ſo (M. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) is it not as meet for a Gentleman, as anie other man?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>No, for I woulde alwaies haue a man called according to the qualities that are in him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>And maie not conſcience bee it? a Gentleman think you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Truely (Gentleman) it is poſſible inough, but it is ſo vnlikelie, that for mine own part, amongſt a great number I could neuer finde manie, that had anie conſcience in them at all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Oh (M. Parſon) I think you ſpeak either of malice, or of affection.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Noe I promiſe you, I ſpeak as I thinke, and if it be true that you are a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman that doth deſerue the name of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, I maruel what you doe here in this place.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Why (M. Parſon) where ſhoulde I be?</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:48"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Mee thinkes it is a greate maruail that you are not preſented to the Queenes Maieſtie, for the greateſt wonder that euer ſhe ſaw.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Why is it ſuch a ſtraunge ſight, to ſee a Gentleman with a good conſcience?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What it is in the Court I cannot tel, but in the countrie I am ſure it is ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, (M. Parſon) you are not ſo ſure of it, as you make youre felfe, for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you haue met with ſome that haue vſed you hardly, yet you may not think but there are other ſome, &amp; that a great many, that are honeſt Gentlemen, and will chuſe rather to looſe their credite, then crack their conſcience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I will not deny but that there bee a few, but to ſay there are many of them in a Country, I will neuer yéeld to it, as long as I liue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>You may not<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 7.1.</note> iudge any (M. par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) but hope the beſt of all, and leaue ſuche matters vnto the iudgement of God, which<note n="*" place="margin">Apoc. 2.23.</note> ſearcheth the heart, and raines of al men, and knoweth thoſe that are his.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Wel, I am contented to hope well of them, although I haue ſmall cauſe to ſay
<pb facs="tcp:176516:48"/>wel of any of them: for I haue not forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, what ſcraps and paringes they haue fetched out of my benefices, and yet forſooth they woulde be counted ſuch as will doe no man harme, and perſwade themſelues, that they are men of very good conſciences: but if this be the fruites of a good conſcience I had as lieue haue a badde conſcience as a good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>There is no doubt of it, but that a good conſcience wil cauſe a good life, and a bad conſience will alwaies ſhewe it ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>That I thinke (in deed) to he verie true: but this grieueth mee, that they will ſay they haue good conſciences, when they are ſtarke naughte, but becauſe you are a Gentleman, &amp; thinke your ſelfe to be a man of a good conſcience, I praye you let mee here (according to your promiſe) howe: ou doe behaue your ſelfe, that I may knowe how to diſcern a good conſcience from a bad and firſt let me be ſo bold to intreat you to ſhew me your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rudition from your childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode vnto this time, and what care your Father had of you in your tender yeeres, to ſee you ſo wel brought vp vntill mans e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:49"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt you muſte obſerue, that my father was a man ordeined to beare the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a iuſtice in the common wealth: and amongſt manie children, I was his eldeſte ſonne; and my father being one that feared God, had no deſire ſo greate, as to bring vp his children in the ſame feare, and becauſe of them al, I was (by nature) moſt able to beare the greateſt charge, his cheefeſt care was to ſee mee wel brought vp, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I might thereby learne to diſcharge my dutie, and the better to bring this to paſſe, I was from my infancy trained vp in learning, &amp; when I came to bee of diſcretion, I was ſente to the Vniuerſitie, that I might the ſooner at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to that which was his deſire, and I being but young of yeares, and wanton by nature, my father for ſo long time wold not ſuffer mee to haue the bridle, but ſpared no charge to keepe me vnder Maſters and tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, that might inforce me to that, which of my ſelf I was vnwilling: &amp; of al times, I thoughte thoſe daies moſte greeuous wherein they wrought beſt for me, and did like of no companie ſo wel as of theirs whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che did moſte hurt me: &amp; in this caſe I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
<pb facs="tcp:176516:49"/>the ſpace of my childiſh yeares: but when I was able to diſcerne good from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and my deareſt friends, from my grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt enemies, and thought thoſe that feared God could giue me beſt counſel: I was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer before ſo vnwilling to take their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, as I was deſirous at laſte to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their admonition, and coulde like of no companie ſo well, as theirs that were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſant with ſuch as were faithfull: ſo that at length, through the prouidence of God, their good inſtructions, and gentle perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, I was gotten ſo far in loue with the law of the Lord, that I coulde ſaie with the Prophet Dauid, that his word was<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto my ſoule, then hony vnto my throte and I founde ſuche pleaſure in the reading thereof, that all the day long my ſtudie was in it, and the more I read, the better I lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the deeper I taſted, the ſweeter I felt it, ſo that from that time to this, I haue alwaies loued the lawe of the Lorde aboue golde or precious ſtone, and am as gladde when I ſee it, as thoſe that haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d great ſpoiles? and when it pleaſeth God, to take awaie my father, and place me in his roome to beare the like office that he did, I kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>we
<pb facs="tcp:176516:50"/>there was<note n="*" place="margin">VViſ. 6.4. Rom. 13.1.</note> no power but was ordeined of God, and that it was my duetie (aboue all thinges) to ſeeke his glorie, &amp; I was taught by the example of Ioſua, that<note n="*" place="margin">Ioſ. 1.8.</note> the lawe of the Lorde ought not to departe oute of my mouth: but that I ſhoulde ſtudie in it day &amp; night, that I might do al thinges that were written therein. Thus did I begin, and ſo doe I continue, and no longer doe I deſire to liue, then this may be found in me, for I know that right<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 116.13.</note> deare in the ſight of the Lorde, is the death of his ſaintes: and that the<note n="*" place="margin">VViſ. 3.11.</note> hope of the vngodlie is vaine, their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours vnfruitfull, and their workes vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, &amp; though they<note n="*" place="margin">VViſ. 3.17.</note> liue long, yet their end ſhal be without honor.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>If all this bee true that you haue ſaide, you haue told me of a ſtrange matter: for it is as hard a thing to finde this which you haue ſpoken of in a man of youre cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, as it is to obteine that which is paſt hope of finding: for you being a magiſtrate and placed in ſo high a roome, are ſet in a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrilous place, and in great danger of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: I know many of your fellowes, that can ſaie well, and make almoſte as faier a ſhew as this, but when they come to ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb facs="tcp:176516:50"/>and their ſecretes are wel knowne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene their wordes and their déedes, there is found greate difference: they can all ſaie they are ſet to execute iuſtice, but when it ſhould be put in practiſe, they ſtraine curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie who ſhall begin: and few loue ſo wel to execute iuſtice, as they doe to neglect it tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughe corruption of bribes, for iuſtice wil be ſolde for many, and the diuell maie haue your ſoules for gaine, and as for your religion, it is al in your lips, and it is to bee found no where elſe, it will bee boughte for goodfellowſhip, and you can frame youre ſelues to euerie companie, amongſt the holy you can counterfaite grauitie, &amp; ſaie as they do, but when you come in companie, where they keepe other rule, you can be as bad as the worſte. I can ſpeake by experience, of more then a good manie of you, that it is but diſſimulation, all that euer you doe, you can prate &amp; talke, and make ſo faire a ſhewe in words, as though they were ſo holie, that the beſt reports were to bad for you: but hee that might open your budgets, and looke in your boxes, and take a viewe of your liues, &amp; your liuings, which you haue purchaſed, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſes that you haue builte, the goods that
<pb facs="tcp:176516:51"/>you poſſeſſe, and the mony that hath bought you all this, which you haue gotten by pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, polling, bribing, vſurie, and ſuch like, ſhould find that if you had your deſeruing, hanging were to good for you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>You are verie plain (M. par) I fear me you begin to wax angry: in anie wiſe be ware of that for the<note n="*" place="margin">Iam. 1.20.</note> wrath of man doth not worke that which is righteous before God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>No (Gentleman) I am not angrie, but I am ſomwhat plaine with you, for you haue bene méetlie plain with me, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am the bolder with you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>But you muſt be aduiſed what you ſaie, and impute theſe faultes whereas you finde them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>So doe I, for I ſpake not to anie, but ſuch as haue theſe faultes in them, but this is the troth of it, you gentlemen are ſo tender that you maie not be touched: you can be contented to talke your pleaſure of other men, but your ſelues take ſcorne to be tolde of your owne faultes, you can ſee moates in othermens eies, &amp; kéepe beames in your owne, you ſtimble at ſtrawes, and leap ouer blockes, you ſtraine at gnats, and ſwallow Camels, you laie heuie burthens
<pb facs="tcp:176516:51"/>vpon other mens ſhoulders, but wil not lift at them your ſelues with one of your fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: and yet you gentlemen neuertheleſſe thinke well of your ſelues, and that there is no fault but in vs of the miniſterie: but he that might make an anatomie of all the partes of you, and ſearche you throughly, ſhould find al theſe, and a great many more faults then I haue ſpoken of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Although you finde theſe faultes in ſome, yet you maie not condemne all, for as there are manie ſuch as you ſpeak of, ſo there are ſome which deale wel and true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie: I meane not to e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cuſe anie that deſerue not commendations, but if my ſelfe were as faultie as thoſe whome you ſpeake of, my conſcience would condemne me, for dealing vniuſtlie: and I confeſſe that it is a hard matter, in ſo greate an office to deale vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightlie: but ſeeing we are called of god to defend his cauſe, we ought to ſet to it head and ſhoulders, that no iote thereof maie fall to the ground: and the harder the matter is to be brought to paſſe, the more paine ought we to take about the ſame, that we may be found faithfull ſeruants, to make a iuſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of ſo great a ſtewardſhip, &amp; I know
<pb facs="tcp:176516:52"/>that in a matter of iuſtice we ought neither to<note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 23.2.</note> reuerence the mightie, nor eſteeme the perſon of the poore to perfect iuſtice, &amp; that<note n="*" place="margin">Leui. 19.15. Exo. 23.8.</note>gifts blinde the eies of the wiſe: and<note n="*" place="margin">Eccle. 40.12.</note> bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing is forbidden, and I haue not forgotten what the wiſe man ſaith of negligent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, heare<note n="*" place="margin">VViſ. 6.2.</note> &amp; learne (ſaith he) ye that be iudges of the earth, giue eare yee that rule the multitudes, and delite in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of people: the power is giuen you of the Lorde, which ſhall trie your workes, and ſearch out your imaginations, how that ye beeing his officers, haue not giuen true iudgement, haue not kept the laws of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, nor walked after the wil of God, this doe I know to be true, and at this doe I quake and tremble: for euen as the<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 123.2.</note> eies of ſeruaunts looke vnto the handes of their maſters, and the eies of a maiden vnto the handes of her miſtreſſe: ſo ought we to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend vpon the Lorde our God: no prince ſo mightie, no eſtate ſo ſtout, but he muſt ſtoup at the Lords beck, and tremble at his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce: nor no man that euer was, is, or ſhall be,<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 14.12.</note> but ſhall once appeare before the maieſticall ſeate of the mightie Iehoua, to acknowledge him to be the onelie Lorde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue
<pb facs="tcp:176516:52"/>all others, and he that will not ſubmit himſelfe, as unworthie to be made his foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole, ſhal one daie find that the wickednes of ſo proude a heart, hath wrought him his vtter deſtruction, &amp; that this fault may not be found amongſt vs, let other mens harms teach vs to beware: proude<note n="*" place="margin">Dan. 5.20.</note> Nabuch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſer, was (for his pride) chaunged from a man to a beaſt, harde harted<note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 14.28.</note> Pharao was (for his diſobedience) drowned in the red ſea.<note n="*" place="margin">2. Chr. 33.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Manaſſes, for his idolatrie was linked with bolts of yron. Saul for his good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents yl wrought was<note n="*" place="margin">1. Sam. 15.28</note> rent from his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Herod for his vaine glory was eaten vp with lice:<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 12.23, Mar. 27.5.</note> and Iudas for his trecherie was giuen ouer to deſperation, who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this, and will not know himſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> What vain man wil ſet himſelfe againſt his God? or what miſerable creature wil not ſubmit him ſelfe to him that made him? Oh that they knewe that God<note n="*" place="margin">Iam 4.6. 1. Pet. 5.5. Luk. 14.12.</note> reſiſteth the proude, and giueth grace vnto the lowly: and that ſuch as humble them ſelues ſhalbe exalted, &amp; ſuch as exalt them ſelues ſhal be brought lowe, Then ſhoulde they be as wiſe as So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon: as faithful as Abraham: as patient as Iob: as iuſt as Ioſua: and be found with
<pb facs="tcp:176516:53"/>Dauid, euen m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n after the lords own hart: for it is God that wil make all his enemies his footeſtoole, and giue vnto wicked Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates a hard<note n="*" place="margin">VViſ. 6.6.</note> iudgement. This is our duetie, looke ſo it as we will, although we be neuer ſo<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 99.1.</note> rebellious, yet hee is king ſtill</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I perceiue (gentleman) that you haue learned by many examples, what you ought to doe, and if you doe as much as you know, you are worthie to bee commended: you haue tolde me of many matters, and ſhewed me many examples, which you ſaie may teach vs wiſdome: but me thinkes you make more adoe then you néede: for I haue heard that if a man loue God aboue al, and his neighbour as himſelfe, he hath done as much as the law doth require.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, and that is true: for out of true loue which we owe vnto God, ſpringeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to his lawes, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loue towards our neighbour: &amp; without loue our other deedes will nothing profite vs (for as Saint Paul ſayth) if we<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Cor. 13.2.</note> had all propheſie, and coulde vnderſtand al ſecretes, and all knowledge: and if we had as much faith as to remoue mountaines, and were as liberal as to giue all our goods to the poore, and our bodyes
<pb facs="tcp:176516:53"/>to the fire, and being without loue it ſhould profite vs nothing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>In deede as you ſay, &amp; as I thinke, that loue is the cheefeſt thing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wee ought to haue in keeping: ſo in my iudgement, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the moſt part of you gentlemen, it is the greateſt thing that is wanting: for your loue doth ſo farre differ from the loue that ought to be amongſt men, that it may better bee compared to the loue amongeſt dogges: for the dogges will goe together, ſleep together, play together, and lye toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as though there were ſuch friendſhip amongſt them, that nothing ſhoulde make them enemies, but in the middeſt of theire familiaritie, if there bee but a bare bone throwne amongſt them, that hee may haue it that can catch it: you ſhal ſee them al goe together by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ares, that amongſt many, one may haue it: ſo is it amongeſt many of you iuſtices and gentlemen, you wil talke, walke, ſleepe, and lye together, as though true loue were in you, but let there be but a bad bargaine, or a poore mans liuing that it maye bee his that can catche it, a man ſhall finde on the ſuddaine your loue to bee wanting, and euerye man will ſeeke to
<pb facs="tcp:176516:54"/>get it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>This that you ſpeake of in deede is too true and of that number there are too manie: and that this couetous minde dothe ſo reigne amongſt vs, doth appeare the litle knowledge they haue in the Lawe of the Lorde, by the which they ſo direct all theire doinges: I woulde wiſhe them to doe as I would my ſelfe, be content with that which their parentes left them, &amp; giue themſelues whollie, to the executing of Iuſtice, &amp; leaue off from purchaſing other mens liuings.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>And are you ſo wel contented (gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman) that you like not of purchaſing the liuinges of other men? if it be true, you are ſuch a one as I thought litle to haue found you, and although I haue ſpoken againſte the pilling and polling of poore men, yet I neuer meant, but that men maie lawfullie buie and ſel ech others liuinges, for is it not lawful think you to buie a peece of land ſometimes, when a man hath his monie ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by him? what woulde you haue them to doe with their monie, if they ſhould not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy it that way?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>I woulde haue them to doe as<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 19.8.</note> Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus did, giue halfe of their goodes to the
<pb facs="tcp:176516:54"/>poore, &amp; if they haue doone anie man wrong reſtore him foure fould.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Bring you that in their heads, and I wil giue you my necke, and I thinke you teach others that leſſon which you wil not learne your ſelfe: for I pray you, could you be contented to giue a way half of your goodes to the poore, and make a reſtitution of the wrong gotten goodes that you poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>If I mighte haue heene ſo happie, to ſee Chriſt in my houſe, as<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 19.5.</note> Eliſeus did in his, that I mighte haue giuen entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſo greate a peere, as ſuch a one as is Lord of heauen and earth, I coulde vpon that condition be contented to giue awaie al my goodes, and take a bag and a ſtaffe, and followe him. But becauſe there is no ſuch commaundemente giuen vs, therefore we are not bounde to it. But to make a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of<note n="*" place="margin">Exo. 22.5.</note> goodes gotten wrongfully, we are ſtraightlie commanded.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>But what ſhall ſuche doe with theire monie, that be good honeſt gentlemen, and haue done no man wrong?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>They ſhoulde take the counſaile, that Tobias gaue to his Sonne: if they haue
<pb facs="tcp:176516:55"/>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Tobit. 4.8.</note>much, they ſhoulde giue liberally, if they haue litle, yet do their diligence gladly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould they giue? there are ſome y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> haue no almes deed in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, how then ſhal they be ſure to giue as they ought?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>S. Paul hath ſet downe a rule that we ought to do good<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 6.10.</note> vnto al men, but ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially vnto thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> are of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſhold of faith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What, is there no other order ſet down in the ſcripture, but that a man muſt giue ſtil? a man may giue ſo long, til hee giue awaie al that he hath, and ſo he maye beg himſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>There is no commaundemente for any man ſo to do: but you may reade in the Goſpel of a poore<note n="*" place="margin">Mark. 12.42. Luk. 21 4.</note> Widowe that did ſo, and Chriſt commended her for the ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Did hee ſo? truelie if I mighte ſee one that did ſo, I woulde counte him verie wiſe, but I had almoſte forgotten to aſke you one queſtion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you what is that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Doe you not thinke that a man may lay his monie to vſurie, and imploy it that way?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>No: I knowe it is<note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 22.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4. Leui 25.36. Deut. 23.9.</note> forbidden, and therefore it ought not to be vſed at al.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:55"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, I think a little, ten of the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, or ſome reaſonable maſter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>If it bee reaſonable it muſt not be at al, for God hath ſaide by the mouthe of his Prophet, that hee ſhal onely bee accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with him, that in lending of his mony,<note n="*" place="margin">Ezech, 18.17 Luk. 6.35.</note>taketh no increaſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Truelie I tel you there are manie wiſe men, that thinke they may take ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what lawfullie and not offend at al.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Then belike, they thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues wiſer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy Ghoſt, and ſo they ſhalbe ſure one daie, to haue a fools reward.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>But I pray you Sir (becauſe you woulde wiſh Gentlemen to giue ouer pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſing of other mens liuinges) do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you not thinke in deede, that they may lawfully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow their monie that waie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>This muche I can tel you, that a man may offende in ſuch dealinges manie waies: and he that doth not vſe it at al, ſhal be ſure not to offend (in the ſame) at all, but to ſay that it is not lawful in any reſpect, I am not able to proue it, but I would ſuch as do loue it, did knowe what the Prophet Eſay ſaith of ſuch matters. Wo (ſaith hee) be vnto thoſe<note n="*" place="margin">Eſai. 5.8.</note> that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine houſe to houſe and
<pb facs="tcp:176516:56"/>lande to lande, and bring their liuinges ſo neere together, that the poore can gette no grounde: do they thinke to dwel vppon the earth alone? this Wo do I heare alwaies ſounde in my eares, and it cauſeth mee to ſtand in awe, fearing leaſt for ſuche an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence it might fal on my ſelfe, and therfore (M. Parſon) to tell you my minde plainlie, and what I thinke of theſe matters: I doe ſo abhorre ſuch couetous men, and ſuche miſerable wringing, as is now a daies to much put in practiſe, that I cannot like of thoſe that vſe it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>You muſt like of them, as the world is now, or elſe few wil like of you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>How many doth diſlike with mee, for diſliking with ſinne, I make no recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: for I ſecke not the praiſe of men, but my whole ſtudie is, that I may knowe beſt, which waye to ſet foorthe the glorie of God, and diſcharge my duetie vnto him, of whome I am placed in office, and I am taught not to<note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 23.2.</note> follow a multitude, to doe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil: &amp; I know the moſt parte goe the wrong waye: and I had rather deale iuſtly by my ſelfe, then deale wickedly with companie: for he that will commit ſinne for company,
<pb facs="tcp:176516:56"/>may chaunce to goe the diuel for companie. If Noah and his companie had been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions with the wicked when the World was ouerflowed with water for the ſinnes of the people, no doubt of it, but Noah and his companie, had bene drowned for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie. If Lot and his houſholde had offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for companie, they had (no doubt) beene burnt with the other Sodomites for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, If Caleb and Ioſua had murmured (againſte God) with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt of the people for comapanie, they had ſurelie haue bene kept out of the Land of promiſe with the reſt for companie, but let this hee oure comforte as it was theirs: that if there be but eight per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in a whole Worlde, but one houſholde in a great citie: but two men amongeſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie thouſand, that feare God, yet when the Lord ſendeth his puniſhments amongſt the people for their ſinne, the righteous ſhal be ſure to haue no hurte: a<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 91.7.</note> thouſande ſhal fal on their left hande, &amp; ten thouſand on their right: &amp; yet there ſhal no harme come nere them. Therefore (M. Parſon) for mine own parte, it is ſo farre from mee to participate with their offences, that I abhor the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of ſuch as liue vngodlie.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:57"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Mee thinkes you are to preſiſe (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a gentleman) it were inough for mee &amp; my fellows, to lead ſuch a life as you ſpeak of, and yet I would not be bounde to liue ſo ſinguler a life for any thing, a man may be holy and to holy, if he be, and if wee ſhoulde make choiſe of no company, but ſuch as are ſo holy, wee may chaunce to ſeeke a greate while, and yet go alone at the laſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>I for my parte had as leaue to bee without companye, as to bee in companye of thoſe that liue wickedlie, for he that tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth pitch<note n="*" place="margin">Eccle. 13.1. 2. Theſ. 3.14. Ephe. 5.7.</note> ſhal bee defiled therewith, and ſuch as are conuerſaunt with the vngodlie, may chance to be infected, with their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous diſeaſes, and S. Paul willeth ſuche as feare God, not to bee companions of the wicked, nor to haue any fellowſhippe with the workes of darkneſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>If the caſe doe ſtand with you, that you wil chuſe rather to bee alone, then in ſuch companie as dothe not like you, and you wil like of none, but thoſe that liue ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuouſly I thinke it ſtoode you vppon to take greate deliberation, in making choiſe of a good wife, ſince the companie of the wicked doe ſo ill like of you.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:57"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>You may well ſuppoſe that to bee true, for ſo was I ſure to finde it, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that amongeſt ſo manie women there are few good, and as Salomon ſaide, that amongſt<note n="*" place="margin">Eccle. 7.30.</note> a thouſand he had not found one, you maie well thinke a good wife harde to be gotten.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What are they ſo ſcarſe as you make them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>I haue tolde you what Salomon ſaid, and he was a man of great wiſedome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Although good women were not plentie in his time, yet there is good reaſon why there ſhoulde bee more liuing in theſe daies then euer there were: for there dyed not a good woman a great while.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Oh (M. Parſon) you ſpeake more then you can prooue: for death doth take the good, as well as the bad, and it was prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the one as well as for the other: but belike you doe not knowe a good woman that you are of that mind.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I praie you Sir, by what tokens ſhall I know a good woman?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>If ſhee be one that feareth God, if ſhe be holie as was Heſter, if ſhee bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant as was Iudeth, if ſhe be vertuous, as
<pb facs="tcp:176516:58"/>was Rebecca: if ſhe be chaſte as was Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanna: if ſhe be obedient as was Sara: if ſhe loue Chriſt and his worde more then al the vanities of the worlde as did Mary: if you find this in a Woman, deubt not of her goodneſſe, but praiſe God for her, and wiſhe her manie fellowes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What muſte ſhee haue all this in her before ſhe be good? What if ſhee haue but two or thrée of theſe vertues, is not that ynough? if ſhe be holie and obedient ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, maie ſhe not be a little curſt, a little couetous, and maie not ſhee plaie the good-fellow a little ſomtimes, when her huſband is out of the waie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>No: ſhe muſt be altogether vertuous or elſe it were as good ſhe were altogeather wicked: for if ſhe wil ſerue God, ſhee muſt ſerue him alone: for he is a ielous God, and wil not part ſtakes with anie: he will haue al or none, &amp; if there be but one ſinne found in a woman, wherby ſhe doth diſhonor god, it is inough to condemne her, although ſhee thinke her ſelf fraught with manie vertues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What do you thinke ſo? I woulde faine know how you can proue that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>I will prooue it by this place of
<pb facs="tcp:176516:58"/>Scripture, which ſaith, they<note n="*" place="margin">Math. 5.19. Iam. 2.10.</note> that offende in one point, are guiltie of the whole law.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>In deede you ſaie true, ſuch a place there is: but yet me thinkes it is harde dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, that when a man or woman hath kept a great manie of the commaundementes a great while, and ſhal goe to the diuel at laſt for the breach of one of them: beleeue me if you wil, if it be true, I thinke there is not a woman in this country, that ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: for I neuer hard of the woman nor yet man, that hath kepte the lawe ſo preciſelie, but that they haue offended one waie or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and what ſhal they then doe, if the caſe do ſo ſtand?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>This maie bee our comfort: that that which of our ſelues wee can not doe, and that part of the lawe which we doe not fulfil, Chriſt<note n="*" place="margin">1. Ioh 2.2.</note> hath done it for vs, if we take hold on him by faith, and truſt in him as our onelie Mediator and Redeemer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>This is wel ſaide, nowe I like you wel, for of that minde haue I alwaies bene, that it is no matter what we doe our ſelues, nor how we liue, for Chriſte by his death hath purchaſed pardon for al.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Oh now I perceiue you are farre
<pb facs="tcp:176516:59"/>deceiued, to thinke you maie liue at your pleaſure, and that Chriſte will be a baude to your ſinne: for Chriſte died not for vs to the intent that we ſhould continue in ſinne, but that we<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 6.4.</note> ſhould die vnto ſinne, and liue vnto righteouſneſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and let no man take ſuch libertie by the death of Chriſt, that he may liue as he liſt, and yet goe for a good Chriſtian: for S. Paule ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">Gal 5.24.</note> they that are Chriſtes haue crucified the fleſhe, with the affections and luſts thereof: and again,<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Tim. 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9.</note> all that will cal on the name of Chriſt maſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from iniquitie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What are you there now? I praie you let vs talke no more of that matter: but let vs returne to our women againe which we had in talke but now: me thought that communication did like me well, I praie you by what tokens ſhall a man knowe a bad woman?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>If ſhe ſerue not the true God, but falſe Gods of her owne inuention, as did<note n="*" place="margin">2. Chr. 5.16.</note>Maacha, whome her owne ſonne Aſa, put from her authority, and burnt the idole that ſhe had made. If ſhe be as very a harlot as<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 39.12.</note>Putyphars wife, which whould haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Whoredome, with her ſeruaunt Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,
<pb facs="tcp:176516:59"/>if he had not beene the honeſter man. Af ſhe be as couetous as<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> Rachell, that was contented to giue another woman leaue to lie by her huſband Iacob, for a little Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drago<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as. If ſhe be ſuch a one as Paul ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of, that do wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der from<note n="*" place="margin">1. Tim. 5.13</note> houſe to houſe idle, and not idle onely? but as a tatler and buſibodie, ſpeaking thinges that are not comly. If ſhe be worldly minded, wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie giuen, &amp; ſo drunken with the ſame, that ſhe ſet more by the carefulnes of the worlde then by Chriſt &amp; his Goſpel: as did<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 10.4.</note> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha, if ſhe be as Popeholy, as the péeuiſhe woman in the Popiſhe time, that could not ſaie their Paternoſter without a payre of beades. If you find anie of theſe in a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, praie for her, that ſhe maie amend her maners, and haue grace to come out of the ſnare of the diuell, of whom ſhee is holden captiue at his pleaſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I praie God amend them all, and now you haue ſhewed me how I ſhal know the difference betweene a good woman and a bad: I praie you let me heare what good councell you would giue vnto your women and maidens, that might be a ſtaie for them in their tender yeares.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:60"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>I would wiſh them aboue al things, firſt to ſeeke to ſerue God, and leade their liues in his feare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and by the example of Sara: (R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uels daughter) to fli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vnto the Lorde in al their diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſſes: and to ſay with her oute of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence:<note n="*" place="margin">Tob. 3.16.</note> thou knoweſt Lord that I had neuer deſire vnto man, but haue kept my ſoule cleane and from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>nely l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt, I haue not kept company with ſuch as paſſe their time in ſporte, neither haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>iade my ſelf par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker with their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> walke in light beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> huſband haue I conſented to take, not for my pleaſure, but in thy feare, and in any wiſe I would withe them to beware of gadding, by the example of<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 34.1.</note> Dina, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Lea, which on a time would needs go abroade, to ſee and to be ſeene, and loſte her virginitie before ſhe came home, let them beware of proud hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and wanton lookes, by the daughters of Sion,<note n="*" place="margin">Eſai. 3.16.</note> which did walk w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtretched out neckes &amp; coy lookes, going &amp; tripping nicely and tinkling with their féet that theſe plagues fal not on them, whiche the Lord promiſed the daughters of Sion: that he would ſhaue their heades, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their filthineſſe, and take away the gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geouſneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:176516:60"/>of their attire, their Caules, and the round tyres, after the faſhion of the Moone, the ſweete perfumes, the bra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lets and the Wimples, the bonnets &amp; the ſlops, the headbandes and the Tablets, the eare ringes and no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eiewels, the coſtly apparel, the vailes, the criſping pinnes, the glaſſes and the fine linnen, the hoods, and the launs and in ſteed of good ſmel giue them ſtinch, and for their girdle a rent, and for wel ſet hatre, baldneſſe, and in ſteed of a ſtomacher a ſackcloth, and for their beautie, ſunbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>But what ſhal they haue for their Dublets? doe you finde that mentioned in the Scriptures?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>No, I neuer did read of it, and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore I thinke there was no abhomination ſo great before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Why, is it an abhomination for a Woman to weare a dublet thinke you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>The holy Ghoſt thought ſo, when he gaue a commaundemente, to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I praie you what commandement is there for it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>This we may find writtten in Deu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronomium,
<pb facs="tcp:176516:61"/>that<note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 22.5.</note> a Woman ought not to weare that which perteineth to a man, nor a man that which perteineth to a woman, for all that doe ſo are abhomination vnto the Lorde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Then by this ſaying, it is no more lawfull for a woman to were a dublet, then it is for a man to weare a Peticoate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>In deed as you ſaie, they be both alike, and both abhominable in the ſight of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke our gentlewomen doe not know this, that they doe (now a daies) ſo much vſe it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Whether they doe or no, I knowe not, but if they doe not, it is through want of knowledge in the worde of God, which is the cauſe of this, and a great manie ſuch faultes, but if there be anie that doe know it, and vſe it, I would wiſh them to leaue it, if they ſet more by the fauour of God, then they do by the pride of a dublet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Some there may bee that will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme themſelues, if they haue committed this fault through ignoraunce, but manie of them I thinke, wil ſtill continue, as fine as a dogge in a dublet.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:61"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Well, let them looke to this, and all other ſuch faults, as they wil aunſwere for it, and becauſe ignorance is the cauſe of manie of theſe faultes, &amp; ſome there be that would frame themſelues to better maners, if they knew which way: I would wiſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euerie morning before they attire them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, to ſet the bible before them as a glaſſe that they maie be ſure to put on ſuch cloths as they maie ſeeme comely in the ſighte of God: and there they ſhal ſee,<note n="*" place="margin">1. Pet. 3.3.</note> the Apoſtle wil tel them, that they muſt beware of em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broidered haire, or hanging on of Golde, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther putting on of gorgeous apparel: and the hid man which is in the heart muſt bee without corruption, of a meeke and quiet ſpirite, which is before God, a thing muche ſet by: and after this maner, in the old time did the holie women, which truſted in God, attire themſelues, let them take heede in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie wiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they put not on pride with their apparel, for<note n="*" place="margin">Iam. 4.6.</note> God reſiſteth the proude, and giueth grace vnto the lowlie. This is the counſel that I woulde wiſhe them to take, which is not mine own aduiſe, but the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the holie ghoſt, which did know what was beſt meete for them: and therefore I
<pb facs="tcp:176516:62"/>would wiſh al ſuch as feare God, gladly to accept it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>In deede I thinke the counſel bee good: and how it wil bee accepted hereafter I cannot tel: but I am ſure that it is nowe, litle or nothing regarded: neither doe I thinke that amongſt the moſte part, it wil be any thing followed: for women wil bee fine and handſome I tel you: ſay you what you wil.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>If they ſet more by the fauoure of God, then they doe by the praiſe of man, let them frame themſelues to that order which God himſelfe by the mouth of his ſeruants hath ſet down, and he wil bleſſe them, and make them ioyful mothers of vertuous children, and ſhal ſpend their daies in hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, and end their liues in peace: if not, they ſhal one daye finde, that their glorie wil be their ſhame, ſuch pride is their vtter deſtruction, and the breach of Gods lawes, their euerlaſting confuſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>They are bound to thanke you for your good wil, but I feare mee a greate ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of them woulde like you better if you had held your peace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>I knowe not, nor I care not what
<pb facs="tcp:176516:62"/>thanks I haue for the ſame, but that which I haue ſaide: is for good wil y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I beare vnto them, and to diſcharge my duetie which I owe vnto God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e you ſir, if a man woulde chuſe a good wife, amongeſt the like of all theſe women whom you haue ſpoken of: by what tokens ſhal ſhe bee knowne?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Saloman doth teach vs, that fauor<note n="*" place="margin">Pro. 31.3.</note> is deceitfull, and beautie is a vaine thing, and a woman that feareth the Lorde is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be praiſed. Therefore to chuſe a good Wife by Salomans aduiſe, is (in a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) to reſpect the feare of God, as the chée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt thing that is to be ſought for.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>And I praie you Sir, haue your ſelfe met with ſo good a one as you ſpeake of?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Truelie it is not for me to anſwere to that queſtion: but ſuch as ſhe is, I prayſe God for her, and this ſhe could ſaie in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hoiſe of a huſband, that ſhe wold non but him that would chuſe a wife for vertue: for hee that marrieth his Wife for riches, promotion, beautie or ſuch like, which are the delights of a corruptible eye, and maye ſoone vaniſh and vade awaie: when the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb facs="tcp:176516:63"/>ſhal want theſe thinges, the good man wil lacke his wife, and for her ſelfe, if ſhee might haue al the worlde in iointer, and a huſband that coulde bring her al world lye delightes, and yet without vertue, is like a painted ſepulchre that is faire withoute, and within ful of deade mens bones. But where the marriage is made for vertue, which doth continue for euer, they ſhal bee ſure alwaies to loue, and liue wel toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>If you haue founde ſo good a Wife, you maie think your ſelfe happie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>I doe confeſſe it, and knowe it to be the greateſt bleſſing that in this worlde man may poſſeſſe. For examples to teache vs what inconueniences wicked women vnto their huſbandes haue wrought.<note n="*" place="margin">3. Kin. 11.4. 3. Kin. 21.9.</note> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons wiues did turne his heart, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to commit idolatrie: wicked Ieza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel wrought the deſtruction of her huſband as wel as herſelfe. Iob his<note n="*" place="margin">Iob. 2.9.</note> wife bid him curſe God and die, and the wiſe man ſaith, that it is better to dwel with a<note n="*" place="margin">Eccle. 25.8.</note> Lion and a Dragon, then with a wicked and a brau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling woman.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>You are verie ful of your Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb facs="tcp:176516:63"/>I maruel how a man of your calling coulde atteine to this knowledge: for you haue manie lets, and a great charge to looke vnto, which (in my iudgement) woulde oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupie ſo much of your time, that you might not haue leaſure to ſtudie for this learning.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>It was my firſt ſtudie, before I had ſo great a charge: to knowe howe I mighte aunſwere it, before I tooke it in hande: for in al my affairs I ought to make the<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of the Lorde my counſellers, that I may be ſure alwaies to bee wel aduiſed of that which I take in hand.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What, you are a Gentleman, and me thinkes this grauetie dothe not become you: for you muſt be luſtie as the world go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth now a daies, or elſe you wil bee little or nothing ſet by.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Howe I am accounted of in the worlde, I ſet no ſtore: for I hunt not after the praiſe of men: if I did, I<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 1.10.</note> could not bee the ſeruaunt of God, I am contented to let the worlde goe as it is, with the vanities thereof, &amp; leaue the idle praiſes of a vaine man, to thoſe that loue them: and my ſelfe doe eſteeme them no better woorth, then a blaſt of winde blown into the ayre, whiche
<pb facs="tcp:176516:64"/>is come vnlooked for, &amp; gone we knowe not whither: but if there be any that wil think euil of mee, for framing a life to liue accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the worde of God: I woulde they knew the daungers are greate, and their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimies more then they are ware of: for by what meanes, they may chaunce to plucke al the powers of heauen and earth aboute their eares, for the cauſe is the Lordes, and although hee do a while<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 50.2. Pro. 12.6</note> wink at their ſin, yet in the end he wil laugh at their deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Therfore I woulde wiſhe them to bee wiſe in time, and be no longer a friende to filthineſſe and an enemie to vertue: but let them thinke it ſufficient to haue ſpente the time paſt of their life: in<note n="*" place="margin">1. Pet. 4.3.</note> wantonneſſe, drunkenneſſe, gluttonie, and ſuch like: and to return, though long firſt, yet at laſt, that the Lord may haue mercie vpon them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay wel: but yet there is a time for al things, I thinke you are not alwaies in your booke: nor ſo holy but that you can be contented to vſe lawful exerciſes, which are fit for a Gentleman, as hauking, hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and ſuch like?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Lawful exerciſes, being lawfully vſed I can very wel like of: and as for hau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="tcp:176516:64"/>and hunting, they are ſuch exerciſes, as many men in theſe daies do make them their occupations: and as the thinges are indifferent, beeing indifferently vſed, ſo as they are now amongſt the moſt part put in practiſe they are ſhamefully abuſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you Sir, let me know what you diſlike in theſe thinges? mee thinkes there is no ſuch fault to be founde therein: I pray you giue me leaue to ſpeake for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for I loue to keepe a Hauke my ſelfe, and courſe a Hare ſometime, me thinkes it is a goodly ſport.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>It is not vnlike, but you loue it wel, for there are ſome of your coate that are ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n loue with theſe thinges, that they haue greater care ouer their Dogges, then for the ſoules of the people.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>But to let that matter paſſe, I pray you let me know what bee the faultes that you finde in hauking and hunting?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>For hunting this I may ſaye, and ſuch as are hound kéepers ſhal bear me wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, that there is as much ſpent, about the feeding of their vile dogges, as woulde fill the bellies of many a poore body, as deere in the ſight of the Lord, as they themſelues.
<pb facs="tcp:176516:65"/>And the time that they beſtowe vainlie, al the daie, al the weeke, a whole moneth, a whole yeare, yea, and ſome their whole life in theſe, and ſuch like vanities, mighte and ought to be ſpent much better. Their vaine talke, their blaſphemous othes, for whiche they ſhal aunſwere, are the fruites of this their pleaſure, which in the end (withoute amendment) wil work them their vtter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Although in manie theſe faultes maie be found, yet there are ſome that can hehaue themſelues better, and vſe none of theſe things whereof you ſpeak.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Some there maie bee of that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you ſpeake of, or elſe they were naught al: but they are ſo few, that amongſt twenti a man ſhal hardlie find two, that can keepe their mouths from curſing, &amp; their tongues from blaſpheming, the glorious name of God: and he that can thinke beſt of himſelf, and hath kept his tong a great while, yet when it is come to that paſſe, that his pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſhall bee tried, as when his houndes are at a fault, or his hauk cannot be ſerued: then he himſelf wil be at a fault, and think the greateſt othe he can inuent, to little to
<pb facs="tcp:176516:65"/>help the matter: and then with ſhame they ſhewe their religion, that they ſet not ſo much by the diſhonouring of their God, as they doe by the rating of a vile Cur. But I woulde wiſhe ſuche faultes to bee looked vnto in time, that they be not ouertaken in their ſinne, and rewarded for their iniquity they haue manie orders to bee obſerued in theſe paſtimes, and many lecinges there is amongſt them for trifles: I wiſh they wold leaue theſe vaine matters, and lece one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother for greater faultes, as curſing, lying ſwearing and ſuche like: that the name of God be not blaſphemed, &amp; in the end, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues for their ſinnes, accordingly rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: for if the Lord fall a lecing of them, he will pay them home, and giue them ſuche ſtripes, as they ſhall feele the ſmart there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of for euer, for let them flatter themſelues, as fayre as they can, and thinke better of themſelues then they do deſerue, yet if their paſtimes be full of abuſe, and their mirth be not in the feare of God, they drawe ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie with coards of vanitie, and ſin as it were with a Cartrope.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>In deed (as you ſaie) it were verie wel, if this that you haue ſpoken of might
<pb facs="tcp:176516:66"/>be put in practiſe, &amp; that this lying, curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and ſwearing, might be vtterlie aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: but yet mee thinkes a Hauking othe ſometimes is a ſmal matter, and they are but Gentlemens faultes, and therefore I thinke they may the better bee borne with all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What, doe you thinke (M. Parſon) that the Lorde doth regarde the perſon of one man more then another for that he can be contented to ſuffer than in a gentleman, which he doth puniſhe in others? No, holde this for an euerlaſting trueth, that w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him there is no<note n="*" place="margin">2. Chr. 19.7. Act. 10.3.4. Rom. 2.11. Ephe. 6.9.</note> reſpect of perſons, but ſuch as continue in well doing ſhall receiue accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: &amp; they that offend his maieſtie (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out amendment) ſhal find no mercy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>But I will tell you (Gentleman) ſome there bee, that are ſo accuſtomed to theſe faultes, that they ran not leaue it if a man woulde hand them: and therefore you muſt beare ſomwhat with the world, or elſe there wilbe no paſtime.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What (M. Parſon) woulde you haue mee to bee a baude to the wickedneſſe of the people, and to ſoothe them in their ſinne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Fye vpon you, fye vpon you, are you
<pb facs="tcp:176516:66"/>a miniſter, &amp; wil vtter ſuch vngodly ſpeech? I perceiue you ſauour of the things that are not of God. And I woulde you knew it, it is ſo farre from me to alowe of their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that I ſeeke by al meanes poſſible, to ſuppreſſe the ſame: for I know it is not law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful for me to ſow<note n="*" place="margin">Ezec. 13.18.</note> pillowes vnder mens el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowes, nor to laugh at their ſinne. If I did I might chance weepe for my wickednes, and be guiltie of their ſinne. Therefore I woulde they al knewe, that ſuche as<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 119. Leu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.11.</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in curſing, it ſhal fal on them ſelues: and that<note n="*" place="margin">Apoc. 21.8.</note> lyinge is forbidden, and they that vſe it ſhal haue their part<note n="*" place="margin">Eccle. 23.12.</note> in that la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e which burneth with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and Brimſtone: &amp; that the<note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 20.7.</note> mouth of the ſwearer, ſle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth the ſoule, and the Lorde will not holde them guiltleſſe that take his name in vaine, now if they thinke it good to ſweare, curſſe, and lye, and loue the puniſhmentes due for the ſame, let them vſe it ſtil, if not, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> learn to feare before the maieſtie of God, &amp; trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at his iudgements: for as the night doth follow the day, ſo doth theſe puniſhmentes, ſo vngodly a life: for ſuch as offend without any ſcare of God, ſhall be puniſhed for euer without repentance: and they y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> neuer leaue
<pb facs="tcp:176516:67"/>their ſinne, ſhall be ſure neuer to bee forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: but becauſe repentaunce is a remedie at all times, and time muſt be taken while it is: I would wiſh it be ſought for while it may be founde, vnleſſe they ſeeke it hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when it will not be gotten.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I perceiue you are verie ſeuere in puniſhing of ſinne where you may beare rule, and therefore I thinke you are a harde maſter to your ſeruauntes, or elſe they are verie good ſeruants to their Maſter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>As for me and my ſeruants, my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is, that we may be ſuch as may ſerue God: ſo ſhall I be ſure to vſe them well, and they ſhall not faile to ſerue me faithfullie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>And are all your houſholde ſuch as feare God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>If they be not, they are not ſuch as may pleaſe me, and if I knewe them to bee otherwiſe, they ſhoulde not remaine in my houſe, for I know where the feare of God is not, that place is<note n="*" place="margin">Pro. 3.33. Deut. 28.16.</note> accurſed, but the dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges of the righteous ſhall euermore bee bleſſed, and to my knowledge I haue not one, but is ſo reformed of his life, that hee doth not giue any example of euill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>If it bee true, you may ſaie more,
<pb facs="tcp:176516:67"/>then any that euer I heard of before, and I praie you what orders haue you taken to bring this to paſſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt I haue according to the<note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 6.7.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, ſhewed them the lawe of the Lorde, that they might knowe what they ought to doe: and if I find anie ſo obſtinate that will not learne, or ſo vngodly that doth refuſe to reforme his life, I reforme my houſe, and ſend him out of the doores: for I knowe the roome of ſuch to bee better then their companie: and that one ſkabbed ſhéepe may marre a whole flocke, and the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the vngodly to be ſo dangerous, as no plague nor peſtilence is ſo infectious: and I haue learned of Dauid, to looke vnto<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 10.16.</note>ſuch as are faithfull in the land that they may dwel with me, and ſuch as feare God, thoſe I make my ſeruants.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe orders in bringing vp of your ſeruants in the feare of God, deſerue great commendations. But if they doe their ſeruice faithfully as it becommeth them, do you keep them continually in the ſeruitude of Egypt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>No: for I am taught to<note n="*" place="margin">Eccle. 7 21. Deut. 15.13.</note> loue a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete ſeruaunt as mine owne ſoule, and not
<pb facs="tcp:176516:68"/>to defraud him of his libertie, nor leaue him a poore man, and it is my duetie to doe vnto my ſeruants, that which<note n="*" place="margin">Colo. 4.1.</note> is iuſt and equall, knowing that meſelf haue a maſter in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Thus (M. Parſon) haue I ſhewed you my bringing vppe, and howe from my Childehoode vnto this daie, I haue lead my life, and of theſe orders if it pleaſe you, I can be contented you ſhal be a part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: and if you be now any better perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, then heretofore, I wil willingly beſtow the charge on you, to finde you meate and drinke, and all other thinges neceſſary for you as long as you liue, if you will accept ſuch intertainment as I can make you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Sir I am bound to thanke you (for your good will) moſte heartelie, but I doe not yet find any ſuch neceſſity, to be charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able vnto any man, as long as I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to diſcharge my ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Oh it gréeueth me to heare you, are you alwaies one manner of man? you haue tolde me that you haue no wife nor child to care for; and what can you more deſire then food and raiment?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>But what neede I become ſubiect to any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when as I maie be maſter of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes
<pb facs="tcp:176516:68"/>my ſelfe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>For any ſubiection at your handes, I neuer meant to looke for, but if you can like of this offer, you ſhal haue a chamber as your owne, a man at your commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and you ſhall fare no worſe then my ſelfe, which I truſt ſhal be ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent either of vs both. Therefore if you can finde in your hearte to forſake your vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie promotion, and liuings vnlawfullie poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed, and becom a new man and ſeruaunt to God, ſaie no longer nay, but take this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer while you maie haue it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>To haue a Chamber in your houſe and to forgoe a houſe of mine owne, is ſo exchaunge the better for the woorſe, and to ſhut my ſelfe in a priſon, wheras I am now at libertie, and whereas you offer mee one man to attend on me, you maie knowe that I now am able to keepe thrée or foure faule fellowes, which are readie at all times to ſerue my tourne: and I am ſo well beloued amongſt my pariſhioners, that ther are few men or their wiues, but are at my comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement to do for me the beſt that they maie: therefore you to counſell mee to leaue all theſe commodities, and bee chargeable to
<pb facs="tcp:176516:69"/>you, is to trouble your ſelfe, and doe me no pleaſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Oh (M. Parſon) I would not wiſhe you to thinke ſo, but that I can be content to be at greater charge, ſo that I might thereby doe you any good. And theſe vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which you account commodities, are nothing but trains of the diuel to trap you in his gin, for he could be contented to giue you all this worlde (if it were his) that hee might haue but your ſoule in the worlde to come: therefore (M. Parſon) I woulde you knew it, that that which I haue ſayde, I wiſh you for the beſt, and that you might be vnburdened of that great charge which is too heauie for you to beare. Oh, let not the loue of money worke the loſſe of your ſoule, but be contented to loſe ſomwhat for Chriſt, which was contented to laie downe his life for you: oh<note n="*" place="margin">VViſ. 1.12.</note> ſeeke not your death in the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of your life: make no tarying to turne vnto the Lorde, and put not of from day to day, vnleſſe his wrath come ſuddenly, and in the time of vengeance he do deſtroy you, doe no longer ſel your ſelfe to ſinne, &amp; this miſerable world, but ſet your affections in heauen, where your redemer liueth for euer.
<pb facs="tcp:176516:69"/>Come awaie from that whoore of Babylon: drinke no longer of her poiſon: leaue of from Papiſtrie, and defie the Pope and al Poperie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Why, I truſt (gentleman) you doe not thinke that I am a Papiſt, for ſo you might prooue me a traitor both to God and the Quéene.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Truelie (M. Parſon) I haue taken you for no other al this while.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Then I perceiue you haue beene farre deceiued, for I would you knewe it, I am as good a Proteſtant as the proudeſt of you al.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What are you ſo? I praie you what proteſtation can you make thereof, that I maie be ſo wel perſuaded of you:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I can eate fleſhe on Fridaies, I care not if there were not one faſting daie in a whole yeare: I can fal to my vittailes al the Lente: I care not if the Pope were hanged, ſo I mighte fare a penie the better for it. I can bee as holy in the Church as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man, although y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh be ſomwhat fraile when I am abroade, and a thouſande ſuch thinges can I doe, which woulde be to long to reherſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:70"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Oh I perceiue you are deceiued of your ſelf, for you are an Epicure out right. What doe you account this to bee a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants life: No, (M. Parſon) a Proteſtaunt is not knowne by theſe marks.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>No? I praye you, howe wil you know a Proteſtant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>If hee profeſſe that there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,<note n="*" place="margin">1. Tim. 2.5.</note>but in the bloud of Chriſt: if the word<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 3.24.</note> of god dwel in him plentifully: if his talke be alwaies of the<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 9.26.</note> commaundements of the Lorde: if his profeſſion and<note n="*" place="margin">Colo 6.7. Deut. 6.7. Rom. 2.13.</note> his life doe agree: if hee loue ſuch as feare God, for his ſake: if the world be<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 15.4. Gal. 5.24.</note> crucified vnto him, and he vnto the world: if he be not hie min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but doth make himſelf equal with thoſe of the lower ſort. If he<note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 3.8.</note> count al the worlde but dung that he may winne Chriſt: if hee loue<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> the lawe of the Lorde aboue golde or pretious ſtone: If he be no<note n="*" place="margin">Ephe. 5.5.</note> whoremonger, no drunkard, no vſurer, no theefe, no ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, no filthie talker, no couetous perſon: If he be no negligent Paſtor: if he be ſory for his ſinnes committed, and doth ſeeke to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a new man: if he loue Chriſt and his Goſpel ſo wel,<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 14.26.</note> that he can be contented to looſe his life for the ſame. If you finde this
<pb facs="tcp:176516:70"/>in a man, knowe him to be a Proteſtant, as wel in deed as in name, for this is required of him that wil be a profeſſour of the goſpel, and bear the name of a Proteſtant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What are there no Proteſtaunts, but ſuch as haue al this in them? then I think there be not manie Proteſtauntes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt a great number of profeſſors.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>In deede I knowe, Chriſtes flocke is a litle flocke: &amp; that it is an eaſier matter to bee called a Proteſtaunt, then prooued a Proteſtant: but yet ſome there are, and that manie more then we knowe which do wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God, in ſpirite and trueth, and are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be heires of the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Of the which number (M. Parſon) I long to finde you one, and if you will once turn vnto Chriſt, he wilbe be merciful vnto you: and there wil bee more ioie of ſo peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent a ſinner, then of<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 15.7.</note> ninety and nine iuſt perſons. If you did know the rewarde you ſhould haue for following of Chriſte: you would make haſte to goe after him: If you did knowe the ioies, that God hath prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for thoſe that loue him, were ſuch as the<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.9.</note> eye hath not ſeene, the eare hath not hard, nether the hart of man hath euer conceiued,
<pb facs="tcp:176516:71"/>you woulde thirſte after them as the Hart doth for the water brooks. If you did knowe howe<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 84.1.</note> amiable are the dwellinges of the Lorde of Hoſtes, your ſoule woulde haue a deſire and longing to enter into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courts of the Lorde, yea your heart and your fleſhe would reioice in the liuing God. If you did know that in his preſence is the<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 16.12.</note> fulnes of ioy, &amp; that at his right hand there are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for euermore: you wil chuſe rather to be a<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 84.11.</note> doore keeper in the houſe of youre God, then to dwel in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tentes of the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. If you did know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorie they ſhal haue in his kingdome, that ſuffer for his ſake in this world, you would ſet more by the<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eb. 11.16.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke of Chriſte, then by al the treaſures of Egipt. Beware of that ſubtil ſerpent the Diuel, which goeth aboute like a<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Pet. 5.8.</note> roaring Lion, readie to deuour you: it is his perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> makes you in loue with this world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and if it lay in him, he would ſaie vnto you, as he did vnto Chriſt, that he<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 4.8.</note> woulde giue you al the kingdomes in the worlde, to fal downe &amp; worſhip him: for riches and other vanities of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, being vnlawfully poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed, are nothing but baites of that ſubtile Serpent, to intrap ſuch as be not warie of
<pb facs="tcp:176516:71"/>him. Therefore as you loue the ſafetie of your ſelf depart from that which is euil: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note> that euerlaſting life is the gift of God, and the reward of ſinne is euerlaſting damnation: and know that one ſweete looſt from Chriſtes cheekes, is better then al the faire countenances of the world: and an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie countenaunce from his face, is able to cruſh al their enimies in peeces. Therfore auoid his diſpleaſure, beware of his wrath, get into his fauor, and continue in his fear and you ſhal ſtand though the earth fal, and ſhal be ſure of the victorie, though al the world were ſet againſt you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>For your good councel I moſt hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telie thank you, &amp; with your gentle perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, you haue greatlie moued me, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I mean to take another order with my ſelf which I truſt ſhal like you wel enough</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you (M. Parſon) let me hear that order.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Thus I doe determine to lay my plot, becauſe it is a feareful thing to fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the handes of the liuing God, and greate dangers are like to befal thoſe that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in their ſinne: I wil take ſuch a order, that I wil not ſpende much, but liue ſparingly a
<pb facs="tcp:176516:72"/>while, vntil I haue gotten a good peece of mony in my purſe, that may maintaine me during my life: and then I wil departe from my liuings, and repent for al matters halfe a dozen yeares hence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>But what if you ſhould chauuce to dye (M. Parſon) before theſe yeares come out?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>In deede that is the worſt, I neuer thought on that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Oh in any wiſe haue care of that, for death commeth manye times vnlooked for, and you are not ſure of your life one houre: and if death ſhould ouertake you in your ſinnes: you are loſt for euer. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I wold wiſh you, not to delay the time any longer, but deale wiſely for your ſelfe while you may: for if you be once gone<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 50.22.</note> no man may deliuer you, nor make agreement vnto God for you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Truely (Gentleman) you ſay ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, &amp; your perſuaſions are verie ſtrong, and if I might be ſure to obteine the fauor of God and inherite the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by ſuche meanes as you haue ſhewed me, and that there were no doubte of it: I could be contented to yeeld vnto you: but I
<pb facs="tcp:176516:72"/>muſt tel you plain, my benefices are ſwéete, and if I ſhould forſake them all, and go to the diuel at laſt, it would grieue me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>To put you oute of doubte for that matter, heare what Chriſte himſelfe ſaith, which is the dore whereby you muſt enter into heauen: whoſoeuer<note n="*" place="margin">Mar. 19.29.</note> (ſaith he) forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth houſe or brethren, father, or mother, wife or children, goodes or landes, for my names ſake, ſhal receiue an hundred folde in this world, and in the world to come, life euerlaſting.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What is ment by that hundred fold? that if I put awaie my benefices, I ſhall haue them againe and manie more? then I care not how ſoone I depart with them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>No, (M. Par.) you muſt not thinke ſo, but this knowe, that God is able to giue you a thouſande times more, as you maie ſee by the example of<note n="*" place="margin">Iob. 42.10.</note> Iob, but the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is this: that you ſhal in this whorlde haue ſuch peace of conſcience, which the vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>godlie are without: that you ſhal ſaie with Paule, you are as<note n="*" place="margin">2. Cor. 6.10.</note> hauing nothing, and yet poſſeſſing all things: and in the world to come, ioies vnſpeakable, in a life that ſhal laſt for euer. Therefore (M. Parſon)
<pb facs="tcp:176516:73"/>think no time ſo happie, as that which you beſtow in procuring of your ſelf that which wil ſtick by you for euer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Oh this comfort is great, and theſe wordes haue ſtroken me to the heart.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>How doe you (M. Par) me thinkes your collour doth begin to change.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Oh, oh, oh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What are you not wel, that you looke ſo ill?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Oh, ſicke, ſicke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>I woulde we had ſome Ginger for you, or a little Aquauitie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Oh I am ſicke, I am ſicke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Wil you ride to ſome towne? and we will ſend your water to ſome phiſition.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Oh, no, al the Phiſitians in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land are not able to cure this diſeaſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Why (M. Parſon) where dothe it greeue you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par</speaker>
               <p>Oh at the heart, at the heart.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen</speaker>
               <p>I maruell what it ſhoulde bee, that doth take you ſo ſuddenly: haue you not ben ſo troubled with it before?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Oh no, I neuer was in this caſe ſince I was borne before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Be contented to tarrie the Lordes
<pb facs="tcp:176516:73"/>leaſure a little while, and you ſhall ſee, that it will mend anon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Oh Lord help me, oh Ieſu help me, God and our Lady helpe me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Oh (M. Parſon) that is very ill ſayde: do you not thinke that God can helpe you of himſelfe but that you muſt intreate our Ladie, to do ſomwhat for you? in ſo ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you haue greatly diſhonored God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Oh, the Lord forgiue it me. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe I haue offended him in it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>God bee praiſed, that you are ſo ſoone reformed. But I maruaile what it thoulde bee, that doth trouble you ſo at this time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Oh it lieth heauie at my heart.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What ſhould it be thinke you that doth lye ſo heauy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Oh it is my ſinnes, which are more then I am able to beare, for now I feel my ſelfe pricked at the heart, with griefe of my former life. Oh Lord be mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ifull vnto me a ſinner. Howe greeuouſly haue I offended ſo louing a father? how wickedly did I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the miniſtery? howe negligently haue I taught, how vitiouſly haue I liued? how many ſoules through my negligence
<pb facs="tcp:176516:74"/>haue gone to the Diuell, and I haue bene careleſſe and taken no thought for them: oh forgiue me theſe mine offences, or take mee out of this vale of miſerye, that I ſinne no more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Oh comfort your ſelfe and knowe, that with the<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 130.7.</note> lord ther is mercy, and with him ther is plenteous redemption: yea like<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 103.13.</note> as a father pitieth his owne child, ſo is the Lord mercifull to them that feare him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Oh how comfortable are theſe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings nowe vnto me? which ſometime I lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not to heare thereof. Oh my benefices, my benefices, that haue wrought mee this wo: Fye vpon them, fye vpon them, fye vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them: Oh I was neuer ſo farre in loue with them, as I do now deteſt and abhorre them. Oh that al dumb doggs, vnpreaching prelates, popiſh prieſts, non reſidentes, and vnlearned miniſters, would learn by mine example to be wiſe in time. Oh that ſuch as can preach woulde preach: and ſuch as can ſay nothing would giue ouer the place whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is vnméete for them: Oh that ſuche as are ſet as Cyties vpon a high hill, woulde preach Chriſte the Lorde, and them ſelues ſeruants: oh that this ſaying were not to
<pb facs="tcp:176516:74"/>true,<note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 2.21.</note> that euery man ſeeketh his owne, &amp; no man that which is Chriſtes: oh that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers might be ſent into the Lordes har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, and loiteres might bee rooted out: Oh that ſuch as know nothing, but to ſhear the Sheepe, and feede themſelues, did nowe knowe ſo much as I doe, for I neuer had ſuch pleaſure in keeping my benefices, as I doe nowe finde ioy, being willing to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe them. You tolde me (Gentleman) that you thought your ſelf happy to come in my company, but I may bleſſe the time that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I ſaw you Oh how much am I bounde to the Lorde, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hath ordeined ſuch a means to worke mee my ſaluation: praiſed be his name therefore.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Oh the Lorde bee praiſed for euer, that now I finde that in you, which long I haue ſought for. My minde did giue mee that the Lord had his worke in you, &amp; now experience doth teach mee, that it is vnfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly true, and I doubte not, but you are now willing to forſake your benefices and to goe home with me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I am more willing to depart with them, then euer I was to haue them: and am ſo out of loue with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that it gréeueth
<pb facs="tcp:176516:75"/>me to think on them and my deſire is, that I were ſo cleane diſcharged of them, that I might neuer here more of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>You ſhall not neede to take anye further care: but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ntent your ſelfe, and you ſhal haue that which is yours, and be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled no longer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>But thinke you not, that I maye haue my monye againe, that I paied for them vnto my Patrons?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>That queſtion is not woroth the aſking, for they wil be farre from making a reſtitution, that they wil not be knowen you paide any thing for them. But I pray you what did your be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſires coſt you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke my three benefices did ſtande me, one way or another, aboute a fiue hundred pounds.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>What did they ſo? Oh vnſatiable. Symmonie: I praie you in what order did they deale with you? and with what ſhame leſſe faces coulde they d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aunde monie for them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I haue of a long time kept ſecrete their counſell, but now I will diſcloſe their pollicie. Firſt you muſt obſerue, that my three benefices, I had of three Patrons, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176516:75"/>the firſt after ſute made vnto him, ſaide hee was contented that I ſhould haue it before another, on this condition, that I would be thankful for the ſame: and it ſhould coſt me nothing: but my friends (he ſaid) were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to beſtow the ſame vpon me: and I ſhould not be priuy of a peny that was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, before the mony came to be paid, and then I ſhould reape the fruites of my bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in two or three yeares after. Another of my patrons would take no mony, for hee knew it to be vnlawfull: but if I would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow a diſh of Angels (of Apples I ſhoulde ſaie) vppon him when the time of the yeare did ſerue, hee was contented I ſhoulde bee heard before another, but the apples muſte be very ripe and as yellowe as golde. My third patron was counted a man of a very good conſcience, and he woulde no mony at any hand, but his wife muſt haue a gowne and that made of Satten, laid with a ſiluer lace, and the coller ſtiffened with as manie olde angels, as came to a hundred pounde: and ſhe was ſo in loue with the ſame, that if it la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in her ſhe would neuer were other faſhion: and when her huſband ſaw it, he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the ſtuffe ſo wel, that he woulde haue
<pb facs="tcp:176516:76"/>a ſuite of apparell of the ſame making: ſo that to make them this gorgeous ſuite of apparel, I was faine my ſelfe to weare a thred bare coate, I knowe not how long.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Oh moſt wicked, and Diueliſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes, is there ſuch chopping and changing buying and ſelling of mens ſouls? but that the mercy of the Lord, is aboue al workes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> for ſo wicked an abhomination, the earth doth not grone vnder vs, as being wery to beare vs. Haue they ſuch ſhifts to dazle the eies of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? or do they think by ſuch means, to eſcape the iudgements of God? Let them know that when the Lord wil make inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition for ſinne, and the ſecretes os al hearts ſhal be opened, this their wickedneſſe ſhall ſhew it ſelfe, and without amendment ſhal not go vnpuniſhed, Oh how happy are you whome God hath drawne from dangerous dealings? your happineſſe is more then I can expreſſe, you haue by theſe meanes got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten heauen and earth on your ſide, the Lord himſelf doth fauor you, the Sunn &amp; Moone will ſhew you a cheereful countenauce: the earth ſhall ſerue for your pleaſure, the dew in the morning wil giue you a ſweet ſauor, the flowers in the field wil caſt you a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant
<pb facs="tcp:176516:76"/>ſmell, The ſtones in the ſtreetes are at league with you, neither is there anye thing vnder the heauens, that ſhal hurt you but all are ſworne to your ſafety: the Lorde ſhall ſend his Angelles to<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 34.7.</note> pitch their tents about you: ſo that al your enemies ſhal doe you no harme, but death it ſelfe ſhall giue you the victorie, when it commeth to playe his part, it ſhall ſet you free from a greate many of miſeries, and<note n="*" place="margin">Apoc. 14.13.</note> place you in an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting happineſſe. But as for ſuche as<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> continue in their wickedneſſe, woe be vnto them, it were better for them, that they had neuer bene born, for their ſtate, is accurſed, and the beſt of them is but<note n="*" place="margin">Mich. 7.4.</note> as a brier, or a rotten ſtake in a thorny hedge, and though they floriſh a while, as doth the flower of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> field, yet ſhal they wither as doth the graſſe and<note n="*" place="margin">Eſai. 51.8.</note> worms ſhal eate them, euen as moths eat cloth and wool: Wo be vnto them that through the ſtubberneſſe of their hearts can not repente, but heape vp for them ſelues wrath, againſt the day of wrath, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the righteous indgement of God,<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 2.5.</note> which will rewarde euery man according to his workes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Then Woe the vnto all Patrons,
<pb facs="tcp:176516:77"/>which buie and ſell benefices.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, and happie are ſuch Patrons, as beſtow them vpon ſuch as are worthie of them, and that take no monie for them, but ſeeke onelie the glorie of God, and the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of their brethren.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parl</speaker>
               <p>Are there ſome ſuch Patrons think you, that doth ſo beſtow their benefices?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, no doubt of it, there are ſome ſuch, and that manie, although becauſe you haue not found them, you think the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Elias thought (whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther was a ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, amongeſt the prophetes of the Lorde) that there had bene none left, that did ſerue the true God, but himſelf, beacuſe he knew them not: but the<note n="*" place="margin">3. Kin. 19.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4.18.</note> Lorde tolde him, that there were ſeuen thouſand, which he had re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerued, that did neuer bowe their knees to <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al.</hi> So no doubt hath he now a remaant, whome he doth preſerue from that ſinne of ſimmonie, and do leaue it as a thing which doth highlie diſpleaſe the Lorde: the which number, I beſeech him dailie to encreaſe: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the feete of the miniſters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aie be<note n="*" place="margin">Eſai. 52.7. Rom. 10.15.</note> beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and themſelues meſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngers, that maie bring glad tidings of peace, and tidinges of good things.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:77"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhall bee counted but a foole a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt my felows, for playing of his part and they will make it a game to laugh at, for dealing in this maner: but the beſt waie is, to giue them leaue, and abide their ſkoffs, with patience, vntil the Lorde roote them out, or giue them heartes of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>You ſaie verie well, it is our parts to<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 27.16.</note> tarrie the Lords leaſure, and be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to bear the railinges of our aduerſaries for a while: theſe daies will not continue for euer, there will come a laughing time for vs, when they ſhal weepe and howle for the miſerie that ſhal come vpon them: and ſhalbe faine (one day) to ſaie of you, this<note n="*" place="margin">VViſ. 3.5.</note> is he whome we ſomtimes had in diriſion: we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ooles thought his life madneſſe, and his end without honor: but lo, how he is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted amongeſt the Sonnes of God, and his portion is amongſt the ſaints, theſe words ſhal the vngodlie ſaie with griefe of heart: when themſelues are tormented, and you ſhalbe comforted, when you ſhal haue ioies vnſpeakable, and they ſhalbe caſt into vtter darkneſſe, where ſhalbe weeping, and gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of téeth, And nowe that you may ſet
<pb facs="tcp:176516:78"/>ſome order concerning your ſelfe, and ſuche ſtuffe as you haue at home; I wil ſend two of my men with you, that ſhal deale for you as they woulde for me, and in hope that it ſhal not be long, before I ſee you againe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I thanke you ſir moſte heartelie, and I praiſe God highlie that haue ſtirred vp ſuch an inſtrument to cal mee to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, I will ride to my benefices, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge my ſelfe clean of them, and with as much ſpeed as I may, I wil waite on you, in the meane time: I pray God bleſſe you, and yours, and continue that good mind in you, which now you are of, that you and I with al our houſholde, maie ſo ſerue God in this tranſitorie worlde, that wee may ioie with him for euer in the world to come.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <p>Amen.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:176516:78"/>
            <head>A godly and neceſſary prayer into this booke.</head>
            <p>O ETERNALL and euerlaſting God, which haſt made thy dwellings aboue the heauens, &amp; by the Scepter of thy mighte, doeſt rule all the powers in the world, all which ſhould ſound to thy praiſe, and redounde to the honour of thy glorious name: we moſt vile wretches, whom thou haſt made of the duſt of the earth, throw down our ſelues here before thy maieſty, as vnworthy to be made thy footeſtoole, ſubmitting our ſelues vnto thee, and ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>knowledging our ſinnes, we appeal to thee for mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye. VVe confeſſe (O Lorde) that our wickedneſſe is great, our miſdeedes many, &amp; our ſinnes innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and thou art iuſt, thy iudgements are ouer all the worlde, and the puniſhments due for our ſinnes are intollerable. Forgiue them, O Lord forgiue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, mollifie our hard hearts, and gyue vs right ſpirites, that we may ſee our ſinne, and learn to tremble be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy maieſty, &amp; fear to offend any longer. Oh be thou fauourable vnto vs, or els we are loſt for euer: If thou be angry, what may make vs merry? if thou be offended, how may we be pleaſed? If vve haue loſt thy fauour, what friendſhip can help vs? If thou withdraw thy grace from vs, what good ſhal our ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches do vs? If thou be not on our ſide, what ſhal we do with the help of man? If we be whole in body &amp; ſick in ſoule, rich in ſubſtance &amp; poore in godlines: haue the worlde at will, and know not how to vſe it: If we haue ſuch liberty to do waht vve vvould, any yet ſo ſinfull to do nothing as vve ſhoulde, Oh the finne of ſo corrupt hearts, what miſerie vvill it
<pb facs="tcp:176516:79"/>bring vs? vvhat vvoe will it vvorke vs? howe many plagues are there ordeined for ſo great ſinnes? and vvhat a continuall paine vvill our vngodly pleaſure purchaſe for vs? O Lorde if thou let vs liue heere a vvhile, in wealth &amp; eaſe, to the end vve ſhal liue for euer hereafter in miſery &amp; wo? alaſſe that euer vve were born, to ſee ſuch wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ul days: oh far be that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs (O Lorde) and continue thy mercy tovvardes vs for euer. VVe confeſſe that our ſinnes haue wel de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued thy vvrath, and our vvickedneſſe, is great y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to prouoke thy anger, and we know that thy mercies already ſhewed vnto vs, haue beene more then our deſeruinges, vve haue alwayes felt thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly affection towardes vs, vvhen we haue ſhewed our ſelues vnnaturall children, and revvarded thee euill for good: Oh lord forgiue it vs, forgiue our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly behauiour, &amp; lay not our ſins to our charge, but continue thy mercy tovvardes vs ſtill. Looke fauourably vppon this Realme, bleſſe va vvith thy goodneſſe, and defende vs from Sathan and all his miniſters, ouerthrow their deueliſh deuices, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvray their vngodly pollices: preſerue our Queene vvhome thou haſt placed ouer vs, let her rule faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in thy feare, make her dayes happy, and ſende her a long life if it be thy good pleaſure, and vvhen this her earthly princely ſtate ſhall ceaſſe, giue her a heauenly kingdome where ſhee may reigne for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, make her counſellers vviſe in thy feare, to giue ſuch councel, as may tende to thy glory: let he no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles know that their honors conſiſteth in thy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Teach magiſtrates to humble themſelues, and ſeeke the aduancement of thy glory, let them know that they are not placed in office by thee, to gouern as they liſt, or do that which ſeemeth good in their
<pb facs="tcp:176516:79"/>owne eyes, but to ſuppreſſe ſinne &amp; ſupport vertue, let them draw their ſwordes to cut downe vice, and imbrace godlines, as that which is onely their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, teach the miniſterie, to teach the trueth vnto their flocke, and ſeeke the ſafety of thy people, and not their owne priuate gayne: let them not be ſuch as can teach others and not them ſelues, that can ſhere the ſheepe, and not feed the flocke, let not the deſire of filthy lucre, make them careleſſe to do their duety, but let the remembrance of thee (which wilt call them to an account) cauſe them to haue a care of their charge. Teach maſters of houſholdes, my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes and Dames, children and ſeruauntes to ſerue thee, and lead their liues in thy feare, O Lord learne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to know that to dwell vnder thy defence, is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be happy, and not to obey thee, is to be accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and to heap vp for our ſelues, wrath againſt the day of wrath, vvhen, euery man ſhall be revvarded according to his vvorkes: let the power of thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie (vvhich canſt vvith a vvorde ſhake all the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvers in heauen and earth) ſtrike ſo deepe into our hearts, that we may ſet more by thy fauour, then all the fayre countenaunces of the world (which are but vaniti) let not any thing be our delight but that vvhich may pleaſe thee, &amp; let nothing make vs ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry but that which doth offend thy maieſty. Alſo we beſeech thee to looke vppon thy vvhole Churche (vvhereſoeuer) with fauour beholde it, comfort the afflicted members therof, deliuer them with ſpeed, or giue them patience to tarry thy leaſure: let them not faint in that good courſe they haue begon that ſuffer for thy truch, but be thou their help in trouble and lay no more vppon them then they are able to beare. And although we at this time here at home,
<pb facs="tcp:176516:80"/>haue not ſo great cauſe to complayne, as many of our brethren in other countries. But thou (O Lord) haſt delt more fauourably vvith vs then with them, yet let vs not be proude of our eſtate, but giue vs heartes of humilitie, to proſtrate our ſelues before thy maieſtie: for vve know that our deſeruings are not ſuch, nor thy hande is not ſo ſhortned, but that thou canſt ſtrike vs as well as them, let not ſo great wickedneſſe lodge in our breſts, that our proſperity ſhoulde make vs to forget thee, for although vve ſleepe now in ſecutitie and thinke our ſelues out of danger, yet thou canſt quickly ſet the nations about vs vpon our eares, and giue vs ouer to a worſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheefe euen amongeſt our ſelues: thou canſt ſoone make a whole man a ſicke body, and of a liuing bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy a dead corps, and all our pleaſures may ſoone be gone, the aduerſitie of one howre may make vs to forget: all our ſinnes haue truly deſerued theſe and greater plagues, but that thy mercy tovvardes vs, hath beene great, vvhich I beſeech thee for euer to continue. Forgiue vs our ſinnes and pardon vs, for thy ſonne Chriſts ſake, quicken vs as thou art wont to do thy choſen, giue vs a taſte of the ioyes of thy kingdome, that vve may knowe it is better to be a dore keeper in thy houſe, then to dwel in the tentes of the wicked &amp; vngodly, let not the vaine delights of this corrupt world lead vs vnto vanity nor let the alterations of this changeable time turne our harts from thee, but teach vs to knovve that thou art al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvayes one and the ſame, &amp; doſt neuer forget ſuch as doe put their truſt in thee. VVe know that thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly care ouer thy children is great, that they ſhal not looſe a haire of their head, but thou wilt knowe how <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:176516:80"/>they come for<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it: oh learn vs for ſo gret loue, to loue thee againe, and feare to offend ſo deare a Father: keep farre from vs the breach of thy laws, couetous mindes, lying lipes, ſwearing tongues, malicious hearts, vnchaſt and vngodly behauiour, which doth offend thee, and prouoke thine anger againſty vs: &amp; beate down our ſtoute ſtomcks, that we may ſtand in awe &amp; feare thy diſpleaſure, that the plagues due for our ſinnes may be turned away from vs. O Lord make vs wiſe in time, pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in our harts a loue to thy iudgements, and alwaies haue im minde that thou which madeſt the eye muſt needs ſee, which madeſt the eare muſt needs heare, and thou which ſea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cheſt the hearts and reins, muſt needs find out our wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. And becauſe of our ſelues we are not able to doe any thing that is good, but prone and apt to all kinde of ſinne and wickedneſſe, we beſeech thee ſo to aſſiſt vs with the ayde and help of thy holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite, that we may through the ſame, do thoſe things vvhich of our ſelues we are not able, that it may be to thy glory and for the health of our owne ſoules. Oh let theſe our praiers pearce the heauens, and enter into thine eares, and giue vs this and all other things neceſſary for vs, from this time to the end of our liues, and after death a life to liue for euer, for thy deare ſonnes ſake, in whoſe name vve beg it of thee in that praier vvhich he himſelfe hath taughte vs, ſaying. Our father. &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
